<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The late act of the convocation at Oxford examined: or, The obit of prelatique Protestancy: occasioning the conversion of W. R. (sometimes of Exeter Colledge in Oxford) to Catholique union</title>
            <author>Rowland, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57744</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219949</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831394</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831394</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35857</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57744)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35857)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2096:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The late act of the convocation at Oxford examined: or, The obit of prelatique Protestancy: occasioning the conversion of W. R. (sometimes of Exeter Colledge in Oxford) to Catholique union</title>
                  <author>Rowland, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64, 73-141, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Henry Hall],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Rouen [i.e. Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: W. R. [i.e. William Rowland].</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from Madan.</note>
                  <note>Text and register continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>With errata at foot of p. 141.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 133 reads: A cursory animadversion upon Henry Fernes treatise, of the division between the English and Romish church upon the Reformation.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Exeter College Library, Oxford University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ferne, Henry. --  Of the division between the English and Romish church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic converts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35857:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35857:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE LATE ACT</hi> OF THE CONVOCATION AT OXFORD Examined: <hi>OR,</hi> The <hi>OBIT</hi> of Prelatique PROTESTANCY: Occaſioning the Converſion of <hi>W.R.</hi> (Sometimes of EXETER Colledge in OXFORD) to Catholique UNION.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 118.59.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Cogitavi vias meas, &amp; converti pedes meos in Teſtimonia tua.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>St. Ambr. Ep. 31. ad. Valent.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Erubeſeat ſenectus, quae ſe emendare non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test: nullus pudor eſt ad meliora tranſire.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Roven,</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35857:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35857:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> NARRATIVE Of the Motives and Effects of this Treatiſe,</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Learned READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene a no leſſe famous then ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated Cuſtome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, for <hi>Converts</hi> to write Apologies, or ſome kinde of Liter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary Expreſſions of their Inductives to Matriculation into
<pb facs="tcp:35857:3"/>the Wombe of Chriſts Church, as St. <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Arnobius</hi> and the reſt, who of <hi>Heathens,</hi> became <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Great <hi>Origen,</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who from ſiding with <hi>Herctiques,</hi> became <hi>Catholiques.</hi> Hence I eſteeme it my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to addreſſe ſome Reaſon to the World, why I left that Body of Chriſtians, where I had beene Baptiz'd, and Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and now incorporate my ſelfe to the Roman Catholique Church, from which our Nation had this laſt age divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>After my younger Studies in the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> I endeavoured to ſeaſon my ſelfe in our greateſt Authours, as Biſhop <hi>Juell,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Morton,</hi> the laſt Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Uſher,</hi> with <hi>Field, White,</hi> and the reſt; whoſe Apothegmes I received, as Oracles without diſpute; and by the pourſuite of them, I began much to admire our Doctrines, and no leſſe to diſeſteeme the <hi>Roman Catholique;</hi> But upon fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther growth in yeares, with <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> I attempted to reach higher, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring, though with great tenderneſſe, to examine our Tenets and Proofes very
<pb facs="tcp:35857:3"/>ſpeciouſly alleadged out of antiquity; I found ſo many adulterated Texts of holy Fathers, eſpecially in Biſhop <hi>Iewell,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Morton,</hi> ſo many (to ſpeake modeſtly) miſinterpreted in the reſt (of which I may opportunely give a liſt) that I could not but bluſh to finde our main Pillers ſo ſtramineous in their very foundations.</p>
            <p>Hence what curioſity had firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited, now Conſcience enforc'd mee earneſtly to a ſerious and deeper ſearch, wherein I reſolved with <hi>Cato,</hi> not to be aſhamed to Learne, as hee Greeke, So I Latine, not according to the vulgar ſtile, but the old pure Roman Language, expreſſed in St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and the reſt of thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours of Chriſtian Rhetorique; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did I omit with old <hi>Plato</hi> to peragrate <hi>Greece, Aegypt</hi> and the Eaſterne parts to finde any holy Gym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſophiſts, who could embowell, not nature, but the Sacred Myſteries of Chriſtianity, which I found not ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dived into at home.</p>
            <p>In my returne from this Seden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Pilgrimage, (wholy ſettled by
<pb facs="tcp:35857:4"/>the re-ſearches of Antiquity in the truth of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and her Tenets) I fell upon this Act of the <hi>Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-Houſe,</hi> the Diſcuſſion whereof I preſent to all underſtandings, not bias'd with the Praejudice of Cuſtomes, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, or Ambition, that they may judge, out of this Summary, what might be ſaid, if I ſhould expatiate upon this ſubject.</p>
            <p>I bluſh not to publiſh the <hi>impulſive cauſe</hi> of my actuall Conjunction to our old Roman Mother Church, to be from this <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Convocation;</hi> for though I was before fully ſatisfied of thoſe old Tenets in a Speculative ſenſe, yet in reduceing my ſelfe to the Practicall part or profeſſion of them, I found many Phanatique Bug-beares, till hapning upon this <hi>Act,</hi> (compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a great Body of our moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men) and evidently ſeeing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtency of the Doctrine here aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted (eſpecially concerning the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of <hi>Traditions</hi>) with our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Tenets, and Poſitions againſt <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques,</hi> I was inavoidably compelled to an actuall, and humble Submiſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:35857:4"/>my will, as well as of my judgement, to the obedience of the Church: And in this my voluntary retirement from the World, I found un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xpectedly in theſe Forraine parts diverſe of both our Univerſities to have taken the riſe of their Converſions from the ſame ground, and to have prevented mee in their Reſolutions herein, which made mee more thankfully to admire the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, in the ſecret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Soules, culled out for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Gregory</hi> (a very learned perſon, and my contemporary in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> in his Preface to his <hi>Opuſcula,</hi> page 17.) hath this ingenuous acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement; <hi>I am ſorry</hi> (ſayes hee) <hi>I have ſo much to accuſe my Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, that ever ſince the Times of</hi> Henry <hi>the eighth, they ſhould goe about in a Maze of Reformation, and not know yet how to get either us, or themſelves out:</hi> And truly who ever does well conſider this <hi>Act of Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and the ſad conſequences of it, will conclude with mee, that there is but one way to get out of this <hi>Maze,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:35857:5"/>and that is by an humble returne to our Mother, the Catholique Church, which the dazled Eyes and ſelfe-bias'd Judgements of the contrivers of that Act could not then diſcerne; But this ſhort Examination of it may I hope contribute ſomething towards their illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Paris</hi> 
                  <date>this 1. of <hi>July,</hi> 1652. <hi>Stilo loci.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35857:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The <hi>OBIT</hi> of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latique Proteſtancy; <hi>OR</hi> The laſt dying words of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, faintly delivered in the Convocation houſe at Oxford, <hi>1.</hi> of <hi>June, 1641.</hi> Conteining their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt the Scottiſh Covenant and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hymiſts</hi> amongſt Phyſitians deſire ſo far to reforme the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the <hi>Galeniſts,</hi> that they neither obſerve the ſame Method
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35857:6"/>nor druggs in their Cures, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in <hi>Paracelſus, Crollius, Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montius</hi> and others; nay they would willingly ſo far be thought to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from them, as that out of that reſpect they aſſume another name, and therefore commonly ſtyle themſelves <hi>Phyloſophos per ignem, Fiery,</hi> that is, hot ſpirited <hi>Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers.</hi> And truly when I looke upon this Conſult and Reſult of the <hi>Convocation</hi> houſe, <hi>Conſiſting of Maſters, Schollars, and other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers &amp; Members of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> as you profeſs, I conceive you have endeavoured ſo far to reforme the Doctrine and manners of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that you neither agree with them, who would be eſteemed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, nor with their and your Mother Church of Rome, either in Doctrine or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline.</p>
            <p>Nay ye have gone ſo far with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35857:6"/>the <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> that ye will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the common name of all the Moderne <hi>Reformers</hi> (as your later Maſters profeſſe) in which all your Progenitors vaunted; namely under the Notion of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> but ye ſtyle your ſelves here <hi>Christians</hi> or <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (with this diſtinctive appellative) <hi>of the Church of England;</hi> Others deny the name wholy, as in our daily congreſſes we experience, ſo that the more Unigenious name is <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan,</hi> which is alſo more uniforme to the Chymiſts hot ſpirited Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy. As therefore ye are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate in place, ſo in nature and name, from all, who rightly, or falfly acknowledge Chriſt, whence at the moſt (according to your owne principles) ye are but Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logically (I feare I might better ſay equivocally) Chriſtians, as it ſignifies a body of people uniform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35857:7"/>profeſſing Chriſt, with the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Church. So that what <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> improperates in <hi>Origens</hi> third booke, would ſurely come home to you: <hi>Nec jam quicquam preter nomen eis commune ſupereſſe, ſi ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vel hoc prae pudore relinquitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us proceed to particulars.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Your firſt Paragraph is of the firſt Article of the Covenant.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Wherein firſt we are not ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, how we can with Judgement ſweare to endeavour to preſerve the Religion of another Kingdome, whereof, as it doth not concerne us to have very much, ſo we profeſſe to have very little underſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Which (ſo far as the occurrents of theſe unhappy times have brought it to our knowledge, and we are able to judge) as in three of the foure ſpecified particulars,</hi> (viz.) <hi>Worſhip,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35857:7"/>Diſcipline and Government, much worſe; and in the fourth, that of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, not at all better, then our own, which we are in the next paſſage of the Article required to reforme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was much of another ſpirit, he earneſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth a moſt hearty ſence of the welfare of all Churches, he hath a Sollicitous care of all: he cryes out, <hi>Who is weake, and I not weake, who is offended and I burne not?</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. He is highly ſenſible not onely of all Churches, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. See him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. how carefull he is to have all ſpeak the ſame thing, <hi>and that there be no diviſion amongst them: but that they be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde and in the ſame judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Reade him in all his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, ſee how he and his fellow labourers, even anxiouſly eſteemed themſelves concerned in all the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35857:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Churches progreſſe in true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and practiſe. See what he ſayes to the <hi>Romans. Chap.</hi> 12. the aime of his Doctrine is, that we muſt rejoyce with the joyfull, weep with the ſad; we muſt mutually feele each others paſſions: we muſt be deeply concerned in our Brethrens ſpirituall affaires chiefly, but ye contrariwiſe profeſſe, <hi>not to be ſo much concerned,</hi> in preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Religion of your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> would have judg'd your title ſurreptitious, with the pretended Mothers, who was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to have the Child quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo that ſhe might rob the true Mother of her infant; ye cauſed indeed the breach in <hi>Scotland</hi> from their Mother of <hi>Rome,</hi> having done that, you profeſſe your ſelves now <hi>not much concern'd</hi> to preſerve her in any Religion.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35857:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ye could not have uſed any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments more forcible, to prove your ſelves not true lively Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſts great Spirituall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſince it is cleare by your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion here, that you are not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated with the common ſpirit of it, <hi>for ye are not concerned,</hi> &amp;c. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> teaching, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. where he profeſſeth to teach peace of Doctrine in all Churches.</p>
               <p>Ye profeſſe alſo, that you differ from them in <hi>Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Philoſophers at <hi>Athens</hi> (however different in their Schooles touching their opinions of the <hi>Deity, Providence,</hi> &amp;c. as appeares in the tenents of the <hi>Platoniſts, Stoiques</hi> and <hi>Peripate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques,</hi> yet) in their Temple, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Worſhip, Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> did far more agree, then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35857:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>you, meeting quietly at their common oblations to God, which ye profeſſe not to be amongſt you.</p>
               <p>Have ye not in this undeniably aboliſhed one Article of the Creed; which is, <hi>Communion of Saints,</hi> and conſequently taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way your very pretence to a Church? Externall Communion conſiſts in uniformity of <hi>Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government,</hi> moſt eſpecially indeed in <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and in this, as you are ſeperated from <hi>Rome</hi> and their whole Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo ye are, (as you profeſſe) from your neighbouring Churches, whence it followes you are not a true Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſpeak not this, as if I were at all ſcandalized at your breaches: <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> treating of Beaſts, calls a Wolfe (though a Peſtilent creature) <hi>animal generoſum,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35857:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>it will not be made tame: I can ſay no leſſe of you, it is generous not to degenerate, all your prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours diſagreed with each other, as <hi>Luther, Zuinglius, Calvin,</hi> and the reſt. <hi>Tertullian</hi> not far from the end of his treatiſe of <hi>Praeſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> will rub you hard upon the gills. <hi>Mentior, ſi non etiam à regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſuis variant inter ſe dum unuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> proinde ſuo arbitrio modulatur quae accepit, quemadmodum de ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrio ea compoſuit illi quae tradidit,</hi> &amp;c. It hath beene alwaies the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome from the beginning that you thus vary from one another, and yet <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks of it, as a thing moſt ridiculous. <hi>I lye,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if it be not true, that they differ from their owne rules,</hi> &amp;c. he was afraid that future ages would not beleeve ſo prodigious a thing, but ſucceeding ages make it appeare even to children. Ye have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35857:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>juſt title not onely to the Wolfe in this point of generoſity, but to the Foxes under <hi>Sampſon,</hi> in biting each other with all viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, and yet agree in your tailes by firing all behinde you, which is Gods Church.</p>
               <p>It's <hi>Cato</hi>'s aphoriſme, <hi>opertet mendacem eſſe memorem:</hi> You have been alſo obſerved to have been in divers tales. At the firſt under <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. your rule was to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to holy Scriptures, determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church or <hi>Generall Councells,</hi> held before the <hi>laſt</hi> 600. yeares, as appears in the Articles of union betwixt you and the <hi>Germans;</hi> In <hi>B. Jewells</hi> time, you confined your ſelves to the <hi>firſt</hi> 600. yeares. After in <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> time to the <hi>firſt</hi> 400. yeares, and now in <hi>D'allie</hi> to the Apoſtles only: And ſo by degrees you creep to your inviſibility, where every
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35857:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>one is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Son without a Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>For the Doctrine you adde as followes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein if hereafter we ſhall find any thing (as upon farther under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thereof it is not impoſſible we may) that may ſeeme to us ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring of Popery, Superſtition, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie or Schiſme, or contrary to ſound Doctrine, or the Power of Godlineſſe; We ſhall be bound by the next Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to endeavour the extirpation, after we have bound our ſelves, by this firſt Article, to the preſervation thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein we already finde ſome things (to our thinking) ſo far tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuperſtition (in accounting Biſhops Anti Chriſtian, and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Ceremonies, unlawfull) and Schiſmes (in making their Diſcipline
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35857:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Government a marke of the true Church, and the ſetting up thereof the erecting of the Church of Chriſt) that it ſeemeth to us more reaſonable that we ſhould call upon them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame, then that they ſhould call upon us to preſerve it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you have toucht the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againe more deeply to the quick, your quarrels in Doctrine are of no leſſe nature, then of <hi>Superſtition and Schiſme:</hi> Thus <hi>Presbytery</hi> and <hi>Prelacy</hi> are at open wars. We heard of the Heralds at armes menacing mutuall defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance at the <hi>Scotts</hi> firſt entring our Countrey, yet there were hopes of an attonement, but this <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> hath rendred them irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his book of Prayer propounds a queſtion worth your knowing. <hi>Quale ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium eſt, à quo ſine pace recedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur?</hi> No peace, no Sacrifice. He
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35857:11"/>indeed inſinuates an old and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant cuſtome of the Catholick Church in a religious embrace of each other in time of Maſſe, which he here calls <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> ſignifying the charity which ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians, but you have profeſſedly caſt away Maſſe and Peace together.</p>
               <p>The cauſes which each of you already alleadge are true enough, but I leave your ſelves to prove them; its more then ſufficient for all good Chriſtians, who tender their ſalvations, not to adhere to either of you, ſince you are ſo far from unity in Doctrine, that your bodies reſpectively need Reformation, as ye confeſſe of them and they of you; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ye have deſtroyed your ſelves wholly; <hi>Firſt,</hi> from the pretence of being one Chriſtian Church, and conſequently any Church,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35857:12"/>according as the univerſall Church teaches us, <hi>I beleeve one holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique and Apoſtolique Church.</hi> If therefore no unity, no Church. And with no leſſe evidence ye have <hi>Secondly</hi> deſtroyed either of you to be a Church, having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared your ſeverall errours in <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Schiſme;</hi> For ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Holy Scriptures, and the conſent of all, eſpecially old Chriſtians; A Congregation, which ſhould generally and ſolemnly teach and profeſſe Superſtition and Schiſme, neither is nor can be a Church of Chriſt, this would ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it inconſiſtent with the light preſented in Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, and conſequently alienate it from Chriſt. This needs no further proofe to a man who hath obſerved the hinges of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>Doth not the whole world alſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35857:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>know by your voluminous wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, that ye have condemned the very <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the Roman Church, as <hi>unlawfull,</hi> and made that amongſt the vulgar people a maine argument of our <hi>Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and now ye ſay it is <hi>Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in the Presbyters to condemne them in you. Ile not preſſe you, for I ſhould preſently caſt you into <hi>Democritus</hi> his Well: Ye wholly forget the force of an Argument called in the Schooles <hi>ad hominem,</hi> drawne from a mans owne prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, as here againſt you.</p>
               <p>Ye goe on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, we are not ſatisfied in the next Branch, concerning the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion in our owne Kingdome, in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government, how we can ſweare to endeavour the ſame, which (without makeing a change therein) cannot be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:35857:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>It is very well noted, that ye cannot reforme without a change. Phyloſophy would laugh at you to attempt a <hi>Reformation</hi> without a proportionable <hi>mutation;</hi> whence it followes, that you have chang'd your Doctrine, whence it further followes, that its falſe; you know <hi>Gamaliels</hi> rule, <hi>if it be of God, it will stand,</hi> ye know then whence yours comes, for if it change, it is not of God. You pretend to reverence the foure firſt generall Councells, heare what the Councell of <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> ſaith, Act. 1. <hi>Sic ſancivit ſancta ſynodus,</hi> &amp;c <hi>Si quis innovat, Anae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema ſit, ſanctorum patrum fidem ſervemus,</hi> &amp;c. you ſee your ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, if you change you are gone, and yet you muſt change. If your Proſelites would without preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice obſerve, how you tumble and toſſe one another in recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call recriminations, in matter of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35857:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe high inconſiſtencies with Chriſtianity, they would relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh ſuch communion. Your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the contrary in order to you, are important, for <hi>it cannot be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Papiſts &amp; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents are equally rejected by the Praela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique party.</note> 
                  <hi>Without mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt ſcandall to the Papiſt, and Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, by yeilding the cauſe, which our Godly Biſhops and Martyrs, and all our learned Divines ever ſince the Reformation, have both by their writings and ſufferings maintained, who have juſtified againſt them both, the Religion establiſhed in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>to be agreeable to the word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>By Juſtifying the Papiſts in the reproaches and ſcorne by them caſt upon our Religion, whoſe uſuall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection it hath been and is, that we know not what our Religion is, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35857:14"/>ſince we left them, we cannot tell where to stay, that our Religion is a Parliamentary Religion, (let us not be blamed, if we call it a Parliament Religion, Parliament Gospell, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Faith.</hi> Harding <hi>Conſul. of Apology,</hi> part 6. cap. 2.</p>
               <p>Theſe are very home, let me a little dilate them.</p>
               <p>To your firſt. You have indeed ſcandalized all the world, and moſt of all thoſe whom ye call Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, by <hi>yeilding the cauſe,</hi> and ſhewing, that hitherto ye have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted them to bloud, to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of cruelties for not adhering to that, which now is confeſſed to be Superſtitious and Schiſmaticall. <hi>Trajan</hi> was a Heathen and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt enemy of Chriſtian Religion, yet he came not neere your cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: He made a law that no <hi>Pourſivants</hi> ſhould ſearch the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or looke after Chriſtians or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35857:14"/>their Prieſts, but onely apprehend them, if they ſhould happen to meet them. But under your reigne, all our houſes (againſt the liberties of free borne Subjects, as was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in Maſter <hi>Pims</hi> caſe) were diſquieted by the very dregs of mankind, continually infeſted with Saint <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Leopards, who the better he treated them, the worſe they were, but as he ſaid, <hi>Iniquitas eorum mea doctrina eſt,</hi> their iniquities taught us pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>This permiſſion even of aſſemblies in point of Religion, eſpecially in the exerciſe of a Religion which was not newly taken up, though different from that which was then in vogue, was by the Senate al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, as that of the Jewes at Rome; Nay <hi>Suetonius</hi> tells us, that even the Chriſtians were tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated to aſſemble. <hi>Euſebius Hiſt.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35857:15"/>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. ſaith, that <hi>Commodus</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> puniſhed even by death, ſuch who accuſed Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, by reaſon of their quietneſſe. And in his third booke, <hi>cap.</hi> 15. he tells how <hi>Nerva</hi> the Emperour did ſet Chriſtians at liberty gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally by publique Proclamation, &amp; hence Saint <hi>John</hi> was freed from <hi>Patmos.</hi> In fine, he recalled all power given to <hi>Pourſuivants</hi> by his predeceſſours. How much more ſhould Chriſtian Senates allow of innocent meetings in celebration of a Religion, which all our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers profeſſed. But ye perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both new and old Religions; I feare the bloud of all thoſe, who have ſuffered death either by hanging, <hi>Loaplanding</hi> (as the <hi>Dutch</hi> call it) famiſhing or ſtarving for Religion, will call for revenge, but we pray with our bleſſed Saviour and his Protomartyr, Saint <hi>Stephen,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35857:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>ne ſtatuas illis hoc peccatum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath alſo taught us <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.5.21. <hi>Be not overcome of evill, but overcome good with evill.</hi> Nay <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelfe in 4. <hi>Eth. cap.</hi> 3. ſaith, <hi>it is a ſigne of magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to forget injuries.</hi> For as it is a marke of a weake Stomack not to be able to digeſt hard meat, ſo it is of a puſillanimous Soule, not to be able to indure a harſh word or harder threats. <hi>Cicero. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Tusc, ques.</hi> (ſpeaking of wiſe mens patience) ſaith, <hi>ſi fortis in perferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, officii ſatis eſt: ut laetetur, non poſtulo.</hi> Theſe Chriſtian wiſe men have gone further even to joy in Perſecutions. <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> when the <hi>Athenians</hi> were conſulting to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in judgement againſt him, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuſpition of ſome impiety in his opinions, departed from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> and removed his Schoole, ſaying to his Schollars, <hi>Diſcedamus
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35857:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>Athenis, ne prebeamus iis ſecundam occaſionem ſceleris, quale prius per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petraverunt in Socratem, neve iteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per impietatem violent Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> Thus tender <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was of Philoſophy and of their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency: but our Chriſtian Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers here have gone further, they think it neceſſary to confirme what they teach by their blood, and therefore will not deſiſt. This Paraphraſe comes not yet home. Ye are ambitious to challenge Martyrs in confirmation of your Prelatique Proteſtancy, but how unhappily, let all men witneſſe even by Maſter <hi>Foxes</hi> adulterate Monuments.</p>
               <p>For firſt, never any dyed for the whole complex or the <hi>Encyclopedia</hi> of your 39. <hi>Articles,</hi> the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof renders an adequate Praelatiſt, this is cleere in all Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: the truth is, it would have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35857:16"/>argued a phrenſie to maintaine thoſe <hi>Articles</hi> by death, which were only made to maintaine you in life; Againe, no man in his wits would expoſe himſelf even to <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of death for matter of <hi>opinion,</hi> which muſt needs involve uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, neither doe your Articles mount any higher, as <hi>Chilingworth</hi> ingenuouſly confeſſeth &amp; therefore ye all profeſſe a fallibility in your owne decrees, which is conſequent enough. In ſome of your <hi>Articles</hi> you agree with us, ſo that if any of yours ſhould dye for thoſe, we might, if it were worth the while, challenge ſuch as well as you, but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. <hi>Tertul.</hi> againſt <hi>Marian,</hi> lib. 4. Saint <hi>Cipr.</hi> to <hi>Antoniatus,</hi> Ep. 52. To <hi>Cornelius,</hi> Ep. 54. &amp;c. S. <hi>Aug.</hi> againſt the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and all the reſt aſſure us, that, <hi>Eſſe Martyr non poteſt, qui in eceleſia dei non eſt.</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:35857:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>No member of Gods Catholique Church, no Martyr, and hereupon the <hi>Novatians,</hi> though ſharply per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by <hi>Macedonius</hi> for the ſame Doctrine concerning the Bleſſed Trinity, for which the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques alſo were, yet the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world never eſteemed them Martyrs.</p>
               <p>Out of this ground it aroſe that none could be acknowledged or venerated, as <hi>Martyrs,</hi> except the Biſhop of the place had fignifyed by writing to the Primate all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars in the proceſſe, and then he declared them to be ſuch, as appeares in S. <hi>Aug. Brevic. Collat. diei</hi> 3. cap. 13. where he ſhewes how <hi>Secundus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Trigiſitan</hi> in <hi>Numidia</hi> ſignified to <hi>Menſurius</hi> Biſhop and Primate, of <hi>Carthage,</hi> the particular paſſages of ſuch, who had been put to death, becauſe they would not obey <hi>Diocleſians</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35857:17"/>in delivering the Sacred Bookes into their profane hands, and <hi>Menſurius</hi> declared them worthy to be celebrated, as Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs: but to others who had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered under the ſame pretence, yet for other defects, hee denied that honour, as appeares there. This ſolemne Act of Declaration was afterwards transferr'd and limited to the <hi>Pope,</hi> being conceived a buſineſſe of high concernment to the whole Church. Truly, the Church hath beene alwayes ſo tender in this, that Councels, as <hi>Eliber. Can.</hi> 60. aſſume this authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to themſelves, and preſcribe Rules in it, as there, if a Chriſtian ſhould be put to Death for having broken Idols, it is forbidden that hee be accounted a Martyr. It muſt bee done with due circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
               <p>And the caſe of St. <hi>Abda</hi> comes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35857:18"/>home to it, hee had pulled downe an Idolatrous Temple, for which Chriſtians commended him not, but his refuſall to rebuild the Temple was judged cauſe enough of Martyrdome, as <hi>Theodor. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 38. ſhewes. There might be raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the firſt, but ſurely the re-building of an Idolatrous Temple, had beene impiety, and therefore was noble to die for it.</p>
               <p>But if you will know what is required to be eſteemed a Martyr in the ſenſe of Catholiques, adviſe with our Authors eſpecially, St. <hi>Thomas</hi> 2.2. <hi>q.</hi> 124. <hi>a.</hi> 40. <hi>&amp;</hi> 50. and our other Divines. If you will further know the great ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe the univerſall Church hath uſed in recording &amp; admitting the Geſts of her undoubted Martyrs, read the 6. Gen. Councell <hi>Can.</hi> 63. which will tell you that the Roman Church will not permit the Acts
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35857:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Martyrs to be read, which have beene written by Heretiques, nay the councell will have ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords to be burnt.</p>
               <p>In ſome <hi>Articles</hi> you agree with the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> in others with the <hi>Independents:</hi> If any have dyed for either of theſe, each of them may come in as well as you, and yet theſe (conſequent to your Principles) yee eſteeme <hi>Separatists,</hi> that is, not capable of being Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</p>
               <p>Againe in ſome <hi>Articles</hi> you differ from us and them, which are the peculiar Tenents of <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiſme,</hi> and for theſe, they and wee know, that never any Man dyed, namely for <hi>your</hi> Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and the adherent Doctrines, Therefore without doubt yee have no Martyrs, no not ſo much as Pſeudo-Martyrs.</p>
               <p>Secondly, you your ſelves in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35857:19"/>time of your Eſpiſcopall Raigne caſt many (beſides <hi>Catholiques</hi>) <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Dungeons, where they dyed, beggard Families with oppreſſures, wherewith they famiſht, cut off Eares, and baniſht ſuch, who adored not your Epiſcopall Idoll; And may not theſe joyne iſſue upon a farre greater title to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, then you? That the Prelatiſts had almoſt intreated the common people into a beliefe of this Fancy, I wonder not; For if wee looke back to the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> who moſt of all repreſent them, as being zealous Prelatiſts, they were ſo ambitious of this honour, that many caſt themſelves into Precipices, and other wayes ſought their owne Death, upon this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, as <hi>Optaetus Milevitanus,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and diverſe others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. I leave you to tell us, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35857:19"/>ſome of your party have not done the like in our memories.</p>
               <p>The renowned <hi>Apollinaris</hi> in <hi>Euſebius l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 15. ſaith of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphrygeans</hi> or <hi>Montanists,</hi> that when all their Arguments were confuted and they driven to a <hi>non plus,</hi> they left diſputing by way of Reaſon, and produced their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, as proofe enough of their errours; Truly the <hi>Prelatists</hi> being reduced to a loſſe in point of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, for they have already confeſſed their domeſtique incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtencies, now (as yee ſee) they begin with them to challenge Martyrs, whom they would take up from all hands, but if wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plume them, by giving to each part their own, as I have toucht, wee ſhall leave them as naked in point of Martyrs, as <hi>Plato's</hi> Cock in point of being a man.</p>
               <p>We might wonder that in every
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35857:20"/>clauſe, even in this your fainting condition, you ſtill ſtrike at the poore <hi>Catholiques,</hi> (Wormes tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den will ſhew their heads, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence) truly you ſeeme to be much of the nature of Foxes, whoſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy is ſo great againſt innocent Lambes, that their Skinnes made into Drummes will by inviſible beames or ſpirits, endeavour the breaking of a Drum made of Lambs Skin; But it recoyles upon you, this Drum being well beaten, will with innocency deſtroy your rangling and jangling diſſonancies. You force us to ſharpen our Pens, and againſt our inclination to give our Inke a tincture of Gall, leſt wee ſhould not ſeeme ſenſible of your frequent ſcornes in this Act. It was S. <hi>Hierem</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> caſe in their conflicts with the <hi>Donatiſts, Pelagians</hi> and the reſt.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tell us of a Houſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35857:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>infeſted with evill ſpirits, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy whereof hee ſent ſome of his Monkes to ſay Maſſe, which preſently diſpelled the Divells, it would be no leſſe efficatious now againſt all ill ſpirits, who infeſt Gods Servants in their quiet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to his Service. The holy Maſſe is able to humble thoſe fictitious Prieſts in <hi>Iamblicus</hi> in his <hi>Treatiſe of Myſteries,</hi> who threatned the Gods to breake the Heavens, and reveale <hi>Iſis</hi> her Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, to ſtop the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sacred Ship, &amp;c. you ſeeme to threaten Gods <hi>Ship,</hi> which is his <hi>Church,</hi> &amp;c. but all ſignifie your imminent deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Your ſecond Reaſon is alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, that <hi>wee know not what your Religion is,</hi> ſince you your ſelves cannot yet agree on it, nor indeed <hi>know where to stay,</hi> ſince yee left us, you rightly conclude
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35857:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>this, and the changes of your <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> of Beleife even in the higheſt myſteries of Doctrine, as of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination,</hi> finall <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from grace and the reſt, &amp;c. too too abundantly declare, that hitherto <hi>you have wandered in falſe and ſtrange Doctrines.</hi> A miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition for all your Proſelites, now after ſo many years to be to ſeeke Reaſons in point of Doctrine, why yee left us, and yet ſeverely puniſhed us to bloud for not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing you.</p>
               <p>Yee aſſumed to your ſelves a magiſteriall power of dictating Divinity to your followers, and yet you are not agreed upon your owne <hi>Tenets,</hi> this is like <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> who ſent to the <hi>Parliament</hi> to know how hee ſhould expound, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum</hi> to his auditors; Thus your own practiſes diſcover and deſtroy
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35857:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>your deſignes, every propoſition uſed in your Pulpits againſt us was <hi>Demonſtratio</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, no reaſon durſt be offred againſt it, and yet now you have deſtroyed all your ſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Touching your additionall Reaſon of our charging you with embracing a Parliament Religion.</head>
               <p>Can you your ſelves call it any other, then Parliamentary? I wonder yee boggle at this, did not a Parliament lay the firſt Stone, when <hi>Hen. the</hi> 8. made his breach from <hi>Rome,</hi> which yee cite after in your Paragraph <hi>to the Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy?</hi> did it not in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> augment that breach in abolition of Maſſe, &amp;c.? Is not the Supreame power over <hi>all Doctrines</hi> by ſeverall Acts transferred by Parliament to the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35857:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Imperiall Crowne of this Realme,</hi> cited in the ſame Paragraph? was it not alſo re-eſtabliſhed by King <hi>James</hi> in the Parliaments? and ſo ever ſince continued to your great griefes. All men know the paſſages of this. Is there any thing believed to this day any further then ſetled by Parliament, as you in your next (<hi>number</hi> 2.) confeſſe? Nay, doe not your poſteriour Writers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that ſettlement of Religion is ſolely to be had from the civill Power? And upon this ground, they teach that Inhabitants in any Countrey ſhould follow the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, how often ſoever changed there, which was the antiquated impiety of <hi>Celſus,</hi> ſtrengthned by him in many examples, and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confuted by <hi>Origen, fol.</hi> 484. <hi>c.</hi> 2. Upon which ſuppoſition, wee might come at laſt to worſhip a <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> inſteed of GOD, as the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35857:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Aegyptians</hi> did, by <hi>Origens</hi> relation <hi>fol.</hi> 485. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>But to prevent ſuch abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> 49.43. foretelling the times and Method of Government under Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Churches Supremacy, as condiſtinct to temporall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality, ſaith, <hi>Kings ſhall bow down to her with their Face toward the Earth, and lick up the duſt of her Feete,</hi> which ſurely will reach to a ſubmiſſion in Doctrines; but this concernes not your imaginary Church; the Prophet, who fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told Chriſts comming, and his true Churches Birth and Progreſſe, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dreamed of ſuch a <hi>Hypocentaur,</hi> as you had framed, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was Catholique nor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant.</p>
               <p>I conceive it therefore the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt pretence you have to pleade your Origin from a Parliament,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35857:23"/>which being ſuppoſed, you will eaſily finde the way of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and deſtruction to bee equally authenticall, becauſe by Act of Parliament; warranted by that Rule <hi>Per eaſdem cauſas aliquid reſolvitur, per quas componitur,</hi> but becauſe this is a Rule amongſt Lawyers; whom you eſteeme no Friends to <hi>Athens,</hi> I doe not urge it; onely remember it is the ſame way, and as far from your Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges to the Convocation Houſe, as from thence to your Colledges, and all is done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>You go on in your Reaſons.</head>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>By a tacite acknowledgment that there is ſome thing in the Doctrine, and worſhip, whereunto their conformity hath beene required, not agreeable to the Word of God, and conſequently juſtifying them both, the one in his Recuſancy, the other in his ſeparation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:35857:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>You well conclude this, for indeed it followes very evidently, being neceſſarily and virtually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the premiſes: If your forme of Faith muſt be changed, ſurely it convinces that wee, not you, have beene in the right, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to Gods Word, which can not change. So that it is cleare that you are the <hi>Separatists</hi> being changed in Doctrine and worſhip, yet here you very prodigally call others <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> as not agreeing with your fancies.</p>
               <p>Why the <hi>Independent</hi> party ſhould be ſtyled <hi>Separatiſts</hi> by you of the <hi>Prelatique,</hi> I know not: The <hi>Independents</hi> indeed juſtly Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from you, and you unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully from us; Why a juſt Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from you ſhould make theſe to be <hi>Sectaries</hi> (as you often ſtile them) or <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> and your unlawfull ſeparation, not more
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35857:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtrongly conclude againſt your ſelves, who firſt ſeparated from your true Mother, they from an Adultereſſe; Let all men judge. I feare you have forgotten the <hi>Ante-Predicaments,</hi> and the Rules of denomination: you have hitherto done with us, as the <hi>Gentiles</hi> did with old <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> when they appointed ſome upon their Theaters, to imitate their Religious Acts in deriſion of Chriſtians, as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> and the reſt relate; But God ſometimes even miraculouſly turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their jeſts into earneſt, as <hi>Baron. To.</hi> 2. <hi>a.</hi> 303. and elſewhere ſhewes in the caſe of <hi>Ardalion</hi> and <hi>Geneſius,</hi> and S. <hi>August. Ep.</hi> 67. of <hi>Dioſcorus.</hi> You have acted our parts at your pleaſure in your Pulpits hitherto, and yee have taught others to doe the like to you: many of yours with <hi>Geneſius</hi> and ſome of your <hi>Dioſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts,</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:35857:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Arch Players, of deriders, have become ſerious imbracers of Catholique truth. It is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt harme we wiſh you all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicetas Choniates</hi> in his Annals under <hi>Manuel Comnenus,</hi> tells of a Magician, who had ſo farre dementated a poore Waterman, that hee broake in pieces his Boat full of Pots and Pans, and ſuch like Veſſells of Earth; The poore man ſeemed to ſee a horrible Serpent creeping towards him, which hee endeavouring to kill, broke all, and then the Serpent vaniſhed. This was done in ſight of all at Court. Methinks much after this manner, you have beene dementated to breake your ſelves off from all Communion with others, eſteeming all <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> where as indeed you made all the breaches, and even in all our ſights and at the Court, as that poore
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35857:25"/>man did, ſtill thinking to preſerve your ſelves by that which was your ruine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>But you goe on.</head>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>By an implyed Confeſſion, that the Lawes formerly made againſt Papiſts, in this Kingdome and all puniſhments by vertue thereof in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon them, were unjuſt, in puniſhing them for refuſing to joyne with us in that forme of worſhip, which our ſelves, as well as they, doe not approve of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far you rightly obſerve; And ſurely it concernes you to thinke ſadly upon it: how many have loſt their Lives, others their Eſtates for not conforming to your unſound Doctrines, which all your Brethren, and almoſt the whole Country are weary of, and therefore urge for change in your
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35857:25"/>Doctrine and Worſhip, as not agreeable to the Word of God. <hi>Julian</hi> was more viſibly puniſhed by God then many Heathen per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Emperours, by reaſon of his Apoſtacy, the crime ſeemed greater in him; I doubt you will bee the like examples of Gods Juſtice, and confeſſe with him, when it is too late, <hi>Viciſti Galilaee.</hi> When wee are firſt entred into <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Schoole, we are taught to proceede in due forme, leſt an acute adverſary ſhould reduce us <hi>ad impoſſibile,</hi> that is, to ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable abſurdity. Truly, you have argued ſo prepoſterouſly that though your Adverſary would not, yee have intricated your ſelves in a ſad labyrinth.</p>
               <p>It was accuſtomarily given out that <hi>Catholiques</hi> were not in time of your Reigne puniſhed for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but for non-conformity
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35857:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>in points of State. But here yee have taken away that Vizard, in holding forth to all the World, that the Lawes were made, and the puniſhments, (in order to thoſe Lawes) inflicted, for <hi>refuſing to joyne in your forme of Worſhip.</hi> You ſee into what a <hi>Dilemma</hi> you are unadviſedly plung'd, me-thinkes you might have made proviſion in your <hi>Convocation Acts</hi> againſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuted Arguments. The truth is your proceeding againſt. <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,</hi> argued the whole Roman Church in your judgements to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a City of Rogues, not <hi>civitas ſancta,</hi> Gods Church, and therefore wee were in all things uſed like and numbred with rogues and thieves.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cynicks,</hi> that they might be like to <hi>Hercules,</hi> fighting againſt the Lyons, aſſumed for their Dreſſe, a Staffe, inſtead of his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35857:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>Club, and an old cloake. Hence the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and their off-ſpring the <hi>Circumcellians</hi> in <hi>Afrique</hi> uſed juſt the ſame: you have beene indeed very formall and more Eccleſiaſtique-like, then your neighbouring <hi>Scots</hi> in your Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall cloakes, but you agreed in your club-law in perſecution of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques</hi> and all others, who could not conforme their conſciences to your <hi>Ganons,</hi> and behaved your ſelves very cynically towards us all, unhappily following your old Friends the <hi>Donatiſts;</hi> though <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaith, that <hi>nothing is ſo voluntary, as Religion,</hi> which without the wills conſent, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. It was therefore eſteemed high gallantry in the Roman Emperours, to impoſe onely ſuch commands upon the <hi>Jewes,</hi> as were conſiſtent with their Religion, as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian</hi> Records.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35857:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               </p>
               <p>None of you are ignorant how much, and how long wee have ſuffred under the heavy imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Gunpowder Treaſon,</hi> a crime ſo highly oppoſite to our Tenets, that to aſſert it lawfull, were hereſy with us. <hi>Nero,</hi> when he had ſet <hi>Rome</hi> on fire, could not eaſier turne the horrour of it upon any, and free himſelfe, then to lay it upon us, as hee did, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the teſtimony of all the Roman Hiſtorians, though they themſelves diſcover his falſneſſe in it: Even thus when the Plot was layd for that horride attempt of the <hi>Gunpowder,</hi> it was eaſily caſt upon us, and to that end a few young deſperate perſons over-reached and drawne into it, that under that colour, wee might all be traduced, whereas the very memory of it is odious to all <hi>Catholiques;</hi> but time diſcovers
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35857:27"/>the moſt ſecret machinations, and will cleare all calumnies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Yet you adventure to goe on:</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Without manifeſt wrong unto our ſelves, our Conſciences, Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Eſtates, in bearing falſe witneſſe againſt our ſelves, and ſundry other wayes: by ſwearing to endeavour to reforme that as corrupt and vicious; Which wee have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly by our perſonall Subſcription, approved as agreeable to Gods word, and have not beene ſince either condemned by our owne Hearts for ſo doing, or convinced in our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by any of our Brethren, that therein we did amiſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Which in our Conſciences, wee are perſwaded not to be in any of the foure specified particulars (as it ſtandeth eſtabliſhed) much leſſe in the whole foure againſt the Word of God.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:35857:28"/>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Which wee verily believe and (as wee thinke upon good grounds) to be in ſundry reſpects much better, and more agreeable to the Word of God, and the practiſe of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, then that, which wee ſhould by the former words of this Article ſweare to preſerve.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Whereunto the Lawes <hi>(Stat. 13. Eliz. 12.)</hi> yet in force require of all ſuch Clerks as ſhall bee admitted to any Benefice the ſignification of their hearty aſſent to bee atteſted openly in the time of Divine Service; before the whole Congregation there preſent, within a limitted time, and that under paine (upon default made) of the loſſe of every ſuch Benefice.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Without manifeſt danger of perjury, this Branch of the Article (to our beſt underſtanding) ſeeming directly contrary</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> To our former Solemne Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35857:28"/>which wee have bound our ſelves neither for Hope, Feare or other respect ever to relinquiſh. Wherein the Doctrine, which wee have vowed to maintaine, by the name of the true Proteſtant Religion expreſſed in the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> We take to be the ſame, which now we are required to endeavour to Reforme and Alter.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> To the Oath of Supremacy, by us alſo taken according to the Lawes of the Realme, and the Statutes of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity in that behalfe, wherein having first testified and declared in our Conſciences, that the Kings Highneſſe is the onely Supreme Governour of this Realme, wee do after Sweare to our power to aſſiſt and defend all Juriſdictions, Priviledges, Preheminences, and Authorities granted or belonging to the Kings Highneſſe, his Haires and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35857:29"/>Succeſſours, or united and annexed to the Imperiall Crowne of this Realme. One of which Priviledges and Preheminences, by an expreſſe. Statute ſo annexed, and that ever <hi>In terminis</hi> in the ſelfe ſame words, in a manner with thoſe uſed in the Oath, is the whole power of Spirituall or Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdiction for the Correction, and Reformation of all manner of Errours and Abuſes in matters Eccleſiaſticall (ſuch Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, Priviledges, Superiorities, and Preheminences Spirituall, and Eccleſiaſticall, as by any, &amp;c. for the Viſitation of the Eccleſiaſticall State and Perſons, and for Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Order and Correction of the ſame, and of all manner of Errors, Heveſies, Schiſmes, Abuſes, Offences, Contempts, and Enormities, ſhall for ever by Authority of this preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> be united, and annexed to the Imperiall Crowne of this
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35857:29"/>Realme, as by the words of the ſaid Statute more at large appeareth. The Oath affording the Propoſition, and the Statute the Aſſumption, wee finde no way how to avoyd the Concluſion. The Statute is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, An Act Reſtoring to the Crowne the ancient Juriſdiction, &amp;c. <hi>1. Eliz. 1.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To theſe in briefe thus.</head>
               <p>I doubt not but many of your weaker Proſelites eſteeme this Diſcourſe ſo harmonious, as to have power to make Stones dance, as they followed <hi>Amphion</hi> to the <hi>Theban Walls,</hi> or to toſſe the lofty <hi>Offa</hi> and <hi>Banchaia,</hi> and take us all off our Legs, as of old at the hearing the <hi>Odryſian Harpe:</hi> But wee'l ponder your Muſick.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If it be not lawfull for you without manifeſt wrong to your
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35857:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>ſelves, Conſciences, Reputation and Eſtates</hi> to reforme your Doctrine. How was it lawfull for the firſt Broachers of your <hi>Articles,</hi> to pretend Reformation of the Doctrines they had ſworne unto under us, did not they beare falſe witneſſe againſt themſelves, and are not you their iſſue conceived in Perjury? It is ingenuouſly done of you, to confeſſe you had a very conſiderable Eye to the loſſe of your <hi>Eſtates,</hi> in refuſing the <hi>Covenant,</hi> though experience now teacheth you, that the <hi>Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> themſelves are not exempted from that loſſe. <hi>Non eſt conſilium contra Dominum,</hi> your policies did not ſucceed. How free were <hi>Catholiques</hi> from this Avarice? They prodigally expoſed all, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to grate upon their Conſciences. This was not obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy but conſtancy, like the old
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35857:30"/>Chriſtians in S. <hi>Baſiles</hi> time, who would not admit the change of a particle, <hi>ſupereſt diſſerere de Syllaba, oum unde caeperit, &amp;c.</hi> No change of Faith with them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Catholiques</hi> were forced (as much as in you lay) to condemne what they were not, nor yet are convinced of in their Judgements, that the former, that is, the old <hi>Catholique Doctrines</hi> are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Gods Word; Wee muſt therefore cry aloud with <hi>Tertullian</hi> (de Preſ. c. 3.) againſt <hi>Hermogenes. Scriptum eſſe doceat Hermogenis officinae,</hi> &amp;c. Shew us where it is written that we muſt forſake ſtated truths for your variable conceits, altogether diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing from Gods word. This plea will deſtroy you wholy, and with all Juſtice reſtore us at leaſt to a quiet condition under the Profeſſion of our old Tenets.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35857:31"/>
                  <hi>Ptolomey</hi> (though of a different profeſſion to both parties,) was thought capable to determine the Schiſmaticall Controverſie of the two Temples of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Garizim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Catholiques</hi> did not onely believe, but knew that their Doctrines were much better, and more agreeable to the Word of God, and the practiſe of the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> then your fancies: And yet were compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led either to ſweare to them, or loſe all. Wiſe men do not onely provide for the preſent in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Lawes,</hi> but foreſee and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent future, and as much as may bee even poſſible dangers. Had yee conſulted with old <hi>Lycur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> hee found other wayes to perennize his owne Lawes, and perſwade an Opinion of their Divine <hi>Origen:</hi> but your <hi>Eutopia</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:35857:31"/>hath deſtroyed it ſelfe by your owne Fundamentall <hi>Lawes,</hi> they are now with full force retorted upon your ſelves, as all men ſee, and conſequently enforce your ruine for want of Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
               <p>Beſides the falſity of your Doctrines in themſelves, you have all the outward Habiliments of Sectaries, by which the old <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt diſcovered their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> deſtroyes <hi>Arianiſme</hi> in his Tract of the Synods of <hi>Arimine,</hi> and <hi>Seleucia</hi> by this moſt certaine Argument. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſacius &amp; Valens, Geminius, cum caeteris ſuis Gregalibus id fecere, quod antea nec factum nec audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt apud Chriſtianos. Cum enim Scripſiſſent eam fidem quam voluerunt, addidere &amp; Conſulatum &amp; menſem, diemque ejus tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, ut omnibus prudentibus palam
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35857:32"/>facerent, non olim ſed nunc demum eorum fidem ſub Conſtantio initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um accepiſſe.</hi> Thus S. <hi>Baſil</hi> (Ep. 82.) and the reſt confuted He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies even by this Extrinſecall conſideration, and it was alwayes amongſt Chriſtians eſteemed ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to aſſigne the Conſulſhip, the time and day of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions. Which of you or us cannot retrive your forme of Faith not onely to the reigne of which Prince, but of the Lord Major under whom it began, even with as much eaſe as this Act of the <hi>Convocation?</hi> The <hi>Pithagorians</hi> did uſe to build Hearſes for ſuch, who ſhould apoſtatize from Philoſophy, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming them no better then dead men; How much more ſhould ſome ſuch courſe bee taken for thoſe, who forſake Chriſtian Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and turne to Hereſies and Errors!
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35857:32"/>
               </p>
               <p>I wonder you doe not bluſh to pretend the practiſe of the <hi>Catholique</hi> Church: Here is <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnantia in adjecto</hi> as Logitians ſpeake, a Catholique Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to <hi>England,</hi> you pretend no further then <hi>England,</hi> for you ſay <hi>true Proteſtant Religion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England; Indeed this Iland hath beene ſtiled <hi>Orbis Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannicus,</hi> a World by it ſelfe, but it is a very little <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> which encompaſeth not this very Iland. (For, <hi>Scotland</hi> is exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by your own Confeſſion.) So that if this Iland were the <hi>World,</hi> it is not <hi>Catholique.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſon why at <hi>Antioch</hi> the Name of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as a Surname to the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in Chriſt; St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in a Diſputation againſt <hi>Arius</hi> ſets downe to bee, becauſe they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35857:33"/>were before called <hi>Diſciples,</hi> which Name alſo <hi>Doſitheus,</hi> one <hi>Judas</hi> and others (as well falſe as true Teachers) gave to their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and therefore the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> for diſtinction would have their <hi>Diſciples</hi> to be ſurnamed <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which was prophecied by <hi>Iſaias e.</hi> 62. <hi>Servientibus mihi vocabitur novum nomen, &amp;c.</hi> yet afterwards <hi>Heretiques</hi> abuſively tooke this Name alſo, and rendred it exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable to the <hi>Pagans,</hi> by their ill lives and abominable Doctrines, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> demonſtrates in his <hi>Apologetico.</hi> Whereupon the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated adjunct of <hi>Catholique</hi> was taken up and appropriated to Orthodox Chriſtians againſt the <hi>Marcionites, Harpocratians,</hi> and after the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and the reſt; of which alſo they were am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious (as appeares often in St. <hi>Auguſtines Collations</hi> with them)
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35857:33"/>even by as much title as you, peruſe him, and acknowledge your ſelves non Suited: the reaſon of this attribute was <hi>univerſality,</hi> as <hi>Origen</hi> declares in his Dialogue, and all the ancient teſtify: <hi>Pacia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> wrote a whole Treatiſe of the very Name <hi>Catholique,</hi> which is yet extant, though hee lived ſomewhat before St. <hi>Hierome.</hi> Out of theſe examine your Title, and you will finde it vaine, trie it by this teſt, and learne to renounce, what yee have unjuſtly uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</p>
               <p>Your laſt plea of perjury was not admitted to <hi>Catholiques,</hi> who adhered to their firſt Tenents in the generall revolt of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, yet you urge it handſomly to convince all your Brethren of high perjury, in taking ſuch an Oath, which you your ſelves judge to be falſe, ſince yee deny
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35857:34"/>that there is ſuch a power in <hi>Parliaments,</hi> as yee ſaid above, and conſequently in the Crowne, being all the pretence you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge; for it was from <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This point of forcing mens Conſciences with Oathes in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of beliefe, is excellently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared (in a Letter written by Sir <hi>Alexander Irving</hi> a Scot, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the 20. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1651. to the Presbytery of <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> and ſince Printed by authority) to bee greater then any other tyranny, namely to make men ſweare that they believe, what the impoſers know, or may preſume they doe not thinke: This is a ſure way to ſend the ſwearers to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, eſpecially if (to compleat their Malice) the Impoſers ſhould preſently kill them, as I hear of a Varlet, who out of revenge
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35857:34"/>made a wretch firſt forſweare his Religion, and then inſtantly ſtabd him, leſt he ſhould live and repent.</p>
               <p>I could wiſh you &amp; others would vouchſafe to reade, not our <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> that were too much labour, but our <hi>Summiſts</hi> at leaſt, to learne what conditions are required in a Lawfull taking, or impoſing Oaths.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>You proceede.</hi> The SECOND ARTICLE OF THE COVENANT.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, is cannot, but affect us with ſome griefe, and amazement to ſee that ancient forme of Church-Government, which wee heartily and (as wee hope) worthily ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as under which our Religion was at firſt ſo orderly without Violence or Tumults, and ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily reformed, and hath ſince ſo long floriſhed with Truth and Peace, to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35857:35"/>the honour, and happineſſe of our own, and the envy and admiration of other Nations, not only</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Endeavoured to be extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, without any reaſon offered to our underſtandings, for which it ſhould be thought neceſſary, or but ſo much as expedient ſo to doe; But alſo</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Ranked with Popery, Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Hereſy, Schiſme and prophaneſſe, which wee unfainedly profeſſe our ſelves to deteſt as much as any others whatſoever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>And that with ſome intimation alſo, as if that Government were ſome way or other ſo contrary to ſound Doctrine, or the power of Godlineſſe, that whoſoever ſhould not endeavour the extirpation thereof, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity partake in other mens ſinnes, which we cannot yet be perſwaded to believe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To your firſt.</head>
               <p>Was not <hi>England</hi> reformed from
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35857:35"/>Infidelity to Chriſtianity without violence or tumult, and ſo continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till <hi>Henry</hi> the Eights rupture, both in body and minde? did it not continue in admiration of all Nations, becauſe it never admitted any Hereſies? was it not endeavor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to bee extirpated without any reaſons offered to our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;? yet let mee alſo tell you that your pretended Reformation came not in, nor continued without violence. At the very firſt, was there not violence offred in the firſt <hi>Parliament</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> began it in <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. time, what courſe was then taken in the choice of <hi>Parliament</hi> men? again what violence in keeping out the Biſhops, who then were neceſſary Members, that the Vote might be carried for ſuppreſſion of <hi>Maſſe,</hi> and eſtabliſhing your <hi>Common-Prayer Book.</hi> And did it not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue by bloud? The onely argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35857:36"/>uſed to induce <hi>Catholique</hi> to adhere to your new Schiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Prelacy, was that, which began and continues the <hi>Alcaron,</hi> which is the Sword, or (which is more ignominious) the Gallowes, Yet you live under thoſe Governours, who promiſe not to exerciſe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence upon Conſciences, which is your happineſſe. But if they ſhould make uſe of your Lawes, and argue with you <hi>ad hominem,</hi> that way out of your principles, there would be title for cruelties enough: yee hare very cloſely followed the ſteps of your predeceſſors the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> whoſe bloudy proxagation of their Hereſies St. <hi>Hierom</hi> in his Treatiſe againſt them towards the end of the third Booke, ſhewes: So does <hi>Oroſius</hi> alſo and St. <hi>Auguſtine, (of the City of God)</hi> which he dedicated to <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> who was mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by them. God forbid that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:35857:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>any <hi>Phalaris</hi> ſhould put you to <hi>Perillus</hi> his puniſhment, recorded in <hi>Ovid.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Et Phalaris tauro violenti memb a Perilli Torruit: in felix imbuit auctor vpus.</q>
               <p>What a number of <hi>penall Lawes</hi> were in your time &amp; by your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, made againſt tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences? and how rigidly put in execution? How many tyrannicall <hi>Sentences</hi> and <hi>Cenſures</hi> did you paſſe in your <hi>high Comm ſſion court,</hi> for meer <hi>Peccadillo's?</hi> What <hi>Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> and <hi>Mulcts</hi> were impoſed on all ſuch as refuſed to be preſent at your adored Service of <hi>Common-Prayer?</hi> which is now become ſo nauſeous to the generality of People, that it is not to be heard of in the whole Nation, unleſſe in ſome occult or remote Crany, and of whoſe <hi>Origin, continuation,</hi> and <hi>Exit,</hi> you may take this as a ſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35857:37"/>that it was eſtabliſhed by a <hi>Parliament</hi> on the 29 of <hi>May,</hi> 1549. and was aboliſh'd on the 26 of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1644. by the like authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Thus long did it, and your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion continue, without <hi>flouriſhing, either to the happineſſe of our own, or to the envy or admiration of any other Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But on the contrary, is it not moſt apparent, that theſe and ſuch like your unchriſtian actions and fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique <hi>Innovations,</hi> were the onely cauſe of all our late troubles?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Hinc illae Lachrymae.</head>
               <p>From this Source hath iſſued a ſtream of bloud, and a fountain of tears in the late warres; Nor can it ſeem ſtrange, that Almighty God ſhould at length unſheath his ſword to revenge the innocent: You know <hi>Haman</hi> was hang'd on the <hi>Gallowes,</hi> which he erected for <hi>Mardocheus:</hi> But wee pray, that you may finde mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:35857:37"/>
               <head>To the Second.</head>
               <p>Was not <hi>Catholike</hi> Religion by you called <hi>Popery,</hi> and ranked with <hi>Superſtation?</hi> &amp;c. and hath it not by your ſelves to this day been ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniated amongſt the common people, that they do yet take it to be really ſo? In ſo much that one of your learned'ſt Prelates (whoſe name out of civility I ſpare, for I fight not againſt perſons, but cauſes) being asked by a grave gentleman of your <hi>Prelatick Church,</hi> why you did accuſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> of ſuch crimes, as <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which ſhe had ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this Nation, and in the whole world, as all Hiſtories witness. Your Biſhop anſwered ingenuouſly, <hi>That this Prelatick Proteſtancy began with lies and ſo it muſt continue.</hi> Hence this Gentleman took his riſe to become <hi>Catholike,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Credidit &amp; domus ejus iota.</note> and all his Family. Let
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35857:38"/>not any man much wonder at this private confeſſion of the Biſhop, for it is very well conſiſtent with what others have taught in publike. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Gregory</hi> in his <hi>Opuſcula</hi> page 145. hath theſe words; <hi>We make Religion but a politike engine;</hi> which being ſuppoſed, the Biſhop would not have had much labour to prove his <hi>Theſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It's pretty to obſerve what ſtrange deviſes Biſhop <hi>Bancroft</hi> and others uſed to raiſe ſchiſmes amongſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, as was confeſsed in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, By this means he thought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Christian name, when out of his envy to the Churches unity, whence he had fallen, he permitted ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſsentions, to be free from cenſure.</hi> You ſee whence they derived their <hi>Machiaveliſme;</hi> but all in vain, we all ſtick to the rock, when their ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy foundation failes. And queſtion
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:35857:38"/>leſſe it had fail'd as ſoon as concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, if the people had not eaſily been carried away with any, though meer appearances of Reformation, and the hope of gain, by the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of religious houſes, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that, <hi>Sparta diu ſtetit, non quod Rex bene imperabat, ſed quia po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus bene parebat.</hi> You are well read in the hiſtory of <hi>Perkin War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beek,</hi> he had ſo long lied in perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating a King, that the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour <hi>Bacon</hi> ſaith, he did at laſt verily think himſelf to be the King. And really I do believe you had ſo long told this untruth of <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,</hi> that many of you began to believe, that we were <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> indeed; your ſerious manner of ſpeaking would almoſt make us think ſo, were not the thing ſo ridiculous; that we ſhould be <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> who onely have deſtroyed <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> to the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:35857:39"/>of the world.</p>
               <p>Who could believe that D. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> ſhould not bluſh to preach ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent an untruth, as that <hi>Catholiques</hi> hold Fornication to be lawfull; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scriptures, Fathers, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, and the very Catechiſmes wherewith we teach our children yet this he ſaid on Sunday the 25. of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1651. at <hi>Lincolns-Inne.</hi> I would not mention ſo high a crime to his diſhonour, if it had not been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in that publique Theater and ſo firſt publiſhed by himſelfe. And by this we ſee what ground the other Biſhop had for his ingenuous Confeſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To your third.</head>
               <p>Still it runs right. Here is <hi>poem talionis,</hi> which God inflicts upon you. Reflect upon this well, and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how juſtly God hath retorted upon you, what your Pulpits belched con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:35857:39"/>againſt us for ſo many years, and through our ſides againſt your and our parents, and againſt the whole Catholique world, in reſpect of which, ye deſerve not the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary title of a Shadow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>But you go on.</head>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>And we deſire it may be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in caſe a Covenant of like form ſhould be tendered to the Citizens of</hi> London, <hi>wherein they ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to ſwear they would ſincerely, really, and conſtantly, without reſpect of perſons, endeavour the extirpation of Treaſon, (the City Government by a Lord Mayor, Aldermen, Sheriffes, Common Councell, and other Officers depending thereon) murther, adultery, theft, coſenage, and whatſoever ſhall be, &amp;c. left they ſhould partake in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſins; whether ſuch a tendry could be looked upon by any Citizen that had the leaſt ſpirit of freedome in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:35857:40"/>him, as an act of juſtice, meekneſs and reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How ſtill it runs alike, and juſtly to be retorted upon you from <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques,</hi> and with ſome notorious advantage: for this plea of yours is but a pretty fancy, and ends in words, but you have gone further with us, we have been publiquely and ignominiouſly hanged with murtherers, thieves, and reputed Traytors; and theſe have been look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon by you, <hi>as acts of juſtice, meekneſs and reaſon;</hi> as appears in my L. of <hi>Canterbury</hi> his Epiſtle to the late King. But we will hear you fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, for Epiſcopall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; we are not ſatisfied how we can with a good conſcience ſwear to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the extirpation thereof; firſt in reſpect of the thing it ſelf; concerning which Government we think we have reaſon to believe;</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:35857:40"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That it is (if not</hi> Jure Divino <hi>in the ſtricteſt ſenſe, that is to ſay, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely commanded by God in his Word) yet of Apoſtolicall Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is to ſay, was establiſhed in the Churches by the Apoſtles, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the mind, and after the example of their Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, and that by vertue of their ordinary power, and authority derived from him, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by him Governours of his Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Or at least, that Epiſcopall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtocracy hath a fairer pretention, and may lay a juster title and claim to a divine juſtification, then any of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forms of Church Government can do; all which yet do pretend thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> (viz.) <hi>that of the Papall Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, that of the Presbyterian Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy, and that of the Independents by particular Congregations, or gathered Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How feebly do theſe (however
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35857:41"/>learned) men argue in this radicall point, which cuts the very ſinews and heart ſtrings of their Idol: their motions are unequall, like a hen, when her head is ſtruck off, they skip and leap inordinately with <hi>If's</hi> and <hi>Ana's.</hi> B. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> at the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> gave a ſhort come off, ſaying, that <hi>the Government by Biſhops was not ſo neceſſary, as to break the peace for it;</hi> yet he ſcruples not to break the peace of the univerſall Church, for things which they all confeſs leſs neceſſary. In fine, all of you are very ſhort in this fundamentall point; I love <hi>Lypſius</hi> his Laconiſme, rather then <hi>Cicero'es</hi> Dilatations; but this muſt be conſidered <hi>promateria ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrata:</hi> this matter needed all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to picks to ſtrengthen it, if you had them; but I ſee your pantry is ſlenderly provided, foraſmuch as concerns your title to Epiſcopacy, which is your aim to defend, I will
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35857:41"/>afterward ſhew the weakneſſe of your title.</p>
               <p>Had you conſulted the Archives of the Univerſity, and retrived the buſineſſe now in hand to <hi>Wickliffs</hi> time and Tenets, you would have found another kind of ſolution re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred of the <hi>Convocation houſe,</hi> and I believe much more ſavouring of well-grounded Divinity, as applied to Epiſcopacy in it ſelfe, not to yours. For the compariſon you make of <hi>Epiſcopall Ariſtocracy,</hi> and <hi>Papall Monarchy,</hi> are termes, which your young Sophiſters call <hi>Oucate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorimaticall,</hi> they ſignifie nothing as to this purpoſe; For the queſtion is not which is beſt, but whether the firſt can be without the laſt; you muſt firſt ſecure us <hi>de re,</hi> then <hi>de modo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For example, there is a controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie betwixt <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſeat of the ſoul is in the head or heart: it were little to their
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:35857:42"/>purpoſe to aſſert one of theſe to be better then the other, as ſeparate from the other in its own nature; but the way to determine it, is from the operations of the ſoule, to ſee firſt if it will give life to one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other; and therefore <hi>Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes</hi> ſaith, that he ſaw a ram walk a little when the head was ſtruck off: Truly this proof will hold in you; you have made a great bluſter for a time, ſince the Popes head was taken off by <hi>Harry</hi> the VIII but ye ſee now you could continue no more then <hi>Averro's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>am,</hi> becauſe your life was from the Pope; and upon this ſuppoſition, the ſecond queſtion ceaſeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Ye go on.</head>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>But we are aſſured by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted teſtimony of antient Records, and later Hiſtories, that this forme of Government hath been continued with
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35857:42"/>ſuch an univerſall, uninterrupted, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtioned ſucceſſion in all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God, and in all the Kingdomes that have beene called Chriſtian throughout the whole world, for fifteen hundred years together, that there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was in all that time any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble oppoſition made thereagainst. That of <hi>Acrius</hi> was the greatest wherein yet there was little conſideration beſide theſe two things; that it grew at the first but out of diſcontent, and gained him at the last but the reputation of an Heretique. From which antiquity and continuance, we have juſt cauſe to fear that to endeavour the extirpation thereof, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Excuſe me that I tell you here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain you ſpeak high words without ſenſe, as they are applied to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Epiſcopacy. It is a great truth, that Gods Church was uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally govern'd by Biſhops; but this is not the queſtion, but whether
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:35857:43"/>your Schiſmaticall Biſhops ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed lawfully from that old Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; that is, whether the Church of God acknowledged Epiſcopacy law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which erected Altar againſt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, which ſtood in diviſion from all Biſhops throughout the reſt of the world, and could not give letters Communicatories to <hi>Rome,</hi> or to the other <hi>Patriarchs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your Propoſition I deny not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it ſelf true; as in the Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where under <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadius, Origen's</hi> books were queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned; the Fathers rejected not ſuch books as wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> found Orthodox, notwithſtanding his others were full of err<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth S. <hi>Hierome Ep.</hi> 75. and S. <hi>Aug. Ep.</hi> 9. followed the ſame method in them, and after the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Apoſtolique. But as ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocally uſe the term <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> as ſignifying your <hi>nothing,</hi> ſo I muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, and connumerate it with your errours.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:35857:43"/>
               <p>Again, you ſtrike upon <hi>Tradition</hi> for <hi>your</hi> Epiſcopacy, wherein you commit a great ſoloeciſm in Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. If it had been for Epiſcopacy in it ſelf, without reſtriction to your Idol, you had come home indeed; but as it was preſented in your pide-coloured tincture, it was never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Ancient, except <hi>Coly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus</hi> and his complices might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the head of your liſt, from whom you have an <hi>Jſchyrian</hi> generation of Prieſts; which S. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> and (as he aſſures us) the generall Councell, and (I am ſure) the whole Church ever ſince con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for ſpurious.</p>
               <p>But in good earneſt, it is ſtrange to ſee with what modeſty you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem a <hi>meer pretenceſ</hi> for as much as concerns your <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> of fifteen hundred years poſſeſſion, to be an invincible plea in this point, and a reall and clear preſcription for ſo
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35857:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>many ages ſhall not hold for all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as moſt undoubtedly there was not any <hi>conſiderable oppoſition</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Maſſe, till <hi>Calvins</hi> time; (<hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> was not ſo impudent as to take it away,) and how he fared in the ſenſe of the whole Church, we all know; and ſo for many more high Articles (of which I ſpeak after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) wherein you are fallen: All men, carefull of their ſouls, will ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider this.</p>
               <p>It was truly and uſually ſaid of an eminent Biſhop of your Order, that he was <hi>Puritanus tantùm non in Epiſcopatu.</hi> The ſame is as truly ſaid of theſe pretenders to Epiſcopacy; that <hi>they condemn Antiquity in all things except Epiſcopacy:</hi> If novelty be not lawfull in this, why in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doctrines, which you relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſht againſt Antiquity? It's not Antiquity, but fancy and ambition you follow, els a true Syllogiſm in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:35857:44"/>the ſame form will always con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
               <p>You put me in mind of the Aſſe, who wreſting <hi>Orpheus</hi> his sharp out of <hi>Apollo's</hi> hand, played ſo ill-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouredly, that the very dogs barked at him. I will not be thought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this to you, yet I muſt needs ſay that you begin to wreſt our divine Arguments out of our hands, and ye handle them ſo unhandſomly and jarringly from all our and your principles, that all ſorts of men will ſee, whence, and how injuriouſly you take them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>You go on.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> —Would give ſuch advantage to the Papiſts who uſually object a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us and our Religion, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of antiquity, and the love of novelty, that we ſhould not be able to wipe off the aſperſion.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Would ſo diminiſh the juſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority due to the conſentient judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:35857:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>and practiſe of the univerſall Church; the beſt Interpreter of Scriptures in things not clearly expreſt;<note place="margin">Reader, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity there is for all ſorts of Chriſtians to recurre to <hi>Tradition.</hi>
                  </note> (for, <hi>Lex currit cum praxi</hi>) that without it we ſhould be at a loſs in ſundry points, both of faith and manners, at this day firmly believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſecurely practiſed by us; when by the Socinians, Anabaptiſts, and other Sectaries, we ſhould be called upon for our proofs. As name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſundry Orthodoxall explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning the Trinity and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality of the perſons in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head againſt the <hi>Arians</hi> and other Heretiques; the number, uſe, and efficacy of Sacraments; the Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of Infants National Churches; the obſervation of the Lords day; and even the Canon of Scripture it ſelfe.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35857:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> In reſpect of our ſelves, we are not ſatisfied, how it can ſtand with the Principles of Juſtice, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, and Humanity, to require the extirpation of Epiſcopall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, (unleſſe it had been firſt clearly demonſtrated to be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) to be ſincerely and really en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured by us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To the firſt.</head>
               <p>Indeed you cannot wipe off the aſperſion, no more then a Blackmore his colour. You have given us a ſtrange advantage; and in this one paſſage put an affront upon all your former abettors. An eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of your order, (being urged with the antiquity of our tenets) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, that if things were to be ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by antiquity, then <hi>ſin</hi> would chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge great pre-eminency. Thus far hath this plea been derided by you. I could fill and foul many ſheets, in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:35857:46"/>giving a ſyllable of your Authors for this. Yet all antient <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Councells</hi> eſteemed this an infallible Plea; and therefore the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as appears in <hi>Athan.</hi> his Epiſtle of the <hi>Nicene Decrees,</hi> cryed, <hi>Ecce nos demonstramus iſtiuſmodi ſententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, à patribus ad patres, quaſi per ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus traditam eſſe.</hi> They eſteemed it enough to ſhew a conſtant deſcent of their faith, and this is our chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge againſt you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To the ſecond.</head>
               <p>I ſee you forget that your 6.20.21. <hi>Articles</hi> exclude all orall <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,</hi> it hath been the maine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended cauſe of ſcandall, and (as ye have judg'd it) moſt fundamentall, that Catholiques plead a neceſſity of Apoſtolicall I raditions with the divine Scriptures. Have not all the books of your Writers to this day been filled in proofe of the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:35857:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>Scriptures?</hi> and yet now e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the higheſt points of Chriſtian Doctrine, you acknowledge a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to have recourſe to <hi>Tradition:</hi> what man could have read this your ſecond reaſon, and not have concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that this Praelatike ſlip had been again inſerted into the old incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible Trunk or Body of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church?</hi> but the truth is, that ſelf-intereſt compells you to ſpeak truth againſt your old Doctrines: this blow hath ſtruck you under the fifth rib; and like the poor Pilgrime of <hi>Hiericho,</hi> layed you wholly on your backs, as objects of pity.</p>
               <p>You ſpecifie here many of the higheſt myſteries, and to omit the reſt; you acknowledge, that the Orthodox explication of the <hi>B. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> cannot be had from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alone without the Church. Have not we then reaſon to confeſſe the Scripture alone not ſufficient? If you
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:35857:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>did ſtand to this truth, there had not been ſuch ſubdiviſions of ſects, who deny the B. <hi>Trinity,</hi> amongſt you. I have not indeed heard of many who embrace <hi>Arrius</hi> his Tenet, that is, that the Son is God, but not co-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall with the Father, nor equall to him, as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſhews that he held; but there are under the lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Praelatique party, who with <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus, Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras,</hi> &amp;c. call in queſtion his Deity, and reſtraine him to his humanity; and hence ſome eminent perſons, taking ſcandall, left you, and are joyn'd to the <hi>Catholike Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, you are not aſhamed to run, though vainly, to <hi>Traditions,</hi> for the chiefeſt grounds of your own Praela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Sect, herein confeſſing, that, Scripture cannot reach them: But to leave this to your ſelves, let me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance more of our Doctrines which you moſt calumniate. What more
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35857:47"/>univerſal Tradition was extant then <hi>Maſſe?</hi> that is the propitiatory Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Body and Bloud of Chriſt, offered daily and perpetually for the living and the dead. Read Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> his Problemes, he tells you, that it was <hi>univerſally</hi> believed, that <hi>Chriſt gave his true Body and Bloud at his laſt Supper.</hi> Ask all the Liturgies ſince Chriſt. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner read them for <hi>Jnvocation of Saints,</hi> and <hi>Prayers for the Dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay that you may be aſſured, ask a Heathen Hiſtorian <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi> he will ſecure you, that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion teacheth <hi>Cultum Sanctorum,</hi> and to make ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to them, as he writes to <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian.</hi> If you bad yet rather have a Schiſmatique of your owne ſtamp, ask <hi>Lucilla</hi> a Patroneſs of the Donatiſts in lib. 1. of <hi>Optatus Millevitan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for prayers for the dead in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:35857:48"/>to remiſſion of debts after this life, before that great day of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall goal-delivery, or laſt fiery pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, it was (as I conceive) pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed always according to the ſenſe of the Church univerſall by the Eaſt and Weſt, and judged very <hi>profitable</hi> by them all. To omit particular Greek and Latine Fathers, it ſeemeth in the Councell of <hi>Florence</hi> to be the ſenſe of the Greek and Latine Church, as appears in the narration of the whole diſpute, printed at <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> in <hi>Holland;</hi> and the definition of the Councell it ſelf ſeems to come exceeding home, where, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining what ſouls come to heaven <hi>before the day of Iudgment</hi> (for that is the queſtion there decided) the Fathers ſpake thus: <hi>Illorum etiam animas, qui poſt baptiſmum ſuſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, nullam omnino peccati maculam incurrerunt, illas etiam quae poſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractam peccati maculam vel in ſuis
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35857:48"/>corperibus, vel eiſdem exuti corpori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus (prout dictum eſt ſuperius) ſunt purgatae, in coelum mox recipi, &amp;c.</hi> Here they ſuppoſe ſome ſouls to be purged before the laſt day, els the diſcourſe is not conſequent, nor to the purpoſe: Which alſo is cleare in Pope <hi>Benedict XI.</hi> his <hi>Extravagant,</hi> which begins <hi>Benedictus Dens, &amp;c.</hi> where, <hi>defining</hi> the ſame truth agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted under <hi>John</hi> 22. his words are, <hi>Si tum erit aliquod purgabile in eiſdem, lamen poſt mortem ſuam purgabunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>etiam ante reſumptionem ſuorum corporum &amp; judicium generale,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt in coelo,</hi> &amp;c. He defines that ſome will be purged before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of their bodies, and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall judgment, and will go to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>This definition opens fully the ſenſe of the definition of <hi>Florence,</hi> which is made in conformity to this, and almoſt in the very ſame words:
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:35857:49"/>ſo that I do not eaſily ſee what can be deſired more. The ſenſe of the old Church S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> declares in his <hi>Enchyridion</hi> to <hi>Laurence,</hi> where ſpeaking of ſuch ſouls, he ſaith, <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to magis minúſve bona pereuntia di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexerunt, tanto tardiùs, citiuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vari.</hi> This clears all: Its true, he leaves the fire of Purgatory ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what diſputable, (which is not yet deſined) but he clears the meaning of Chriſtians in their durance there; and indeed tells us, what the old Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Liturgies, and Councells, ſignified in their degrees and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of helping the dead by ſuffrages, which was, that anſwerably to their demerits, they might, <hi>tardiùs citiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve ſalvari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There were many Foundations in this Nation made piouſly by your and our Predeceſſouis for the dead, which you perverted to prophane uſes, as maintaining wives and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:35857:49"/>with manifeſt neglect, and even profeſſed contempt of praying for the dead, as holding it unprofitable and uſeleſſe, contrary to all anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; wherein you committed theft and ſacriledge according to the Canons <hi>Concilii Vaſenſis; Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co quippiam rapere furtum eſt, &amp; eccleſia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fraudare ſacrilegium:</hi> and the Canon ſpea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of this very mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter largely. And the fourth <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Carthage c.</hi> 95. ſaith, <hi>Qui oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones defunctorum aut negant eccleſiis, aut cum difficultate reddunt tanquam egentium necatores, excommunicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> They are excommunicated as murtherers. Other Synods are as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, which I omit, theſe ſignifying ſufficiently the ſenſe of the old Church.</p>
               <p>See your friends of <hi>Magdeburg,</hi> for theſe and for the reſt of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, wherein you differ from us, whether antiquity did not ackdow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:35857:50"/>them. Ask <hi>B. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> and the reſt, who have any ingenuity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, whether the Popes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy was not acknowledg'd? Read the hiſtory of the famous <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corinth,</hi> in <hi>Euſebius</hi> and S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> who lived under <hi>Antoninus Verus;</hi> you know how neere this was to the Apoſtles, you will conclude of how great autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> were in thoſe firſt daies, when their commands (ſignified in their Epiſtles) were (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven amongſt the Greeks) publiſhed in the Churches in time of Divine Service by the Biſhops; and S. <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> (in <hi>Panar. hereſi.</hi> 30. againſt the <hi>Ebions</hi>) witneſſeth, that S. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> his <hi>Encycles</hi> were ſolemnly read in Churches, which was an act of high reverence, far from your ſcorn of that Supreme Seat. See for this and all other points, even all true Generall Councells to this day,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35857:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>they will let you ſee clearly. Ask <hi>Perkins,</hi> and your moſt eminent Writers, whether almoſt all the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, for which you ſeparte from us, were not held above 1300. years.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Traditions</hi> prove Epiſcopacy, they will as well prove the reſt. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this ſole Paragraph deſtroyes all your Praelatique Proteſtancy, and renders you to your firſt condition of <hi>inviſibility,</hi> where ye lay for 1500. years hidden, not in <hi>Abrahams</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome: But if you can faine any exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, it muſt be in ſome occult re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles, or crany holes of your own fancies. <hi>Plato's</hi> Ideas, though fanatique enough, never reacht you, but <hi>Luther</hi> being in drink, and his fancy weakned, firſt began to dream of you, though confuſedly. I know many of you are well acquainted with <hi>Gyges</hi> his Ring, which renders you inviſible at pleaſure, but you
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:35857:51"/>have not the perfect uſe of it, els you could as well make your ſelves viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all the world. Your old friend <hi>B. White</hi> and <hi>B. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> laboured much to get this art, but unſucceſſefully, I muſt needs touch this main point a little farther.</p>
               <p>I more commend <hi>Monſieur D'al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Chillingworth,</hi> and all his ſchools ingenuity, who though they ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the grounds of Chriſtianity, yet they far more conſequently deny the Fathers to have that authority, which Catholiques and the General Councells univerſally give them, in clearing points of faith (as in the firſt four, where they were alledged, examined, and accordingly Faith declared by their authorities, and ſo in every Councell hitherto in point of Chriſtian Doctrine) then you, who play faſt and looſe. Here you pretend neceſſity and high authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for <hi>Tradition,</hi> which muſt needs
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:35857:51"/>be conveighed by them to us, and in all your works (as I have noted, and as all know) you have cryed out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, as not being neceſſary. Thus you fight and contradict each other, and your ſelves in theſe fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls.</p>
               <p>I remember <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Timaeo</hi> tells of an <hi>Aegyptian Priest,</hi> who thus ſpoke to <hi>Solon; O Solon! Solon! vos quidem Graeci pueri ſemper estis, ſenex autem Graecorum nemo, nulla eſt enim apud vos diſciplina quae ſenio incanuerit.</hi> Will not this come home to you? if your years are to be numbred with the continuance of your doctrines, ſurely you will never be very aged.</p>
               <p>Since you have toucht this point of the Fathers, let me put in one obſervation, whereby any ignorant perſon may judge, whether the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (of how great or little autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſoever they are with you) were
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:35857:52"/>
                  <hi>Proteſtants</hi> or <hi>Catholiques,</hi> without diſcuſſing their many volumes, which only learned men can maſter; that is, look upon their perſons, ſee what they were in themſelves, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe their lives, without their books; was not S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> confeſſedly a Prieſt?<note place="margin">l. <hi>9.</hi> Conf. c. <hi>11, 12, 13,</hi> &amp;c. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ita ejus à Poſſidio. De moribus ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Cath. Ep. <hi>90.92.45.</hi> &amp; aliis.</note> unmarried? did he not ſay <hi>Maſſe?</hi> that is, offer up the body and bloud of Chriſt in ſacrifice for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and the dead? was he not Biſhop of <hi>Hippo?</hi> did he not inſtitute a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous order of Monks? did he not in fact acknowledge the Pope to be Head of the Church, and his Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our? &amp;c. Whether could he with theſe be a <hi>Proteſtant?</hi> Nay, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were not many upon far leſſe grouds often convicted at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> for Popiſh Prieſts, and in your
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:35857:52"/>reign hang'd and quartered. Take the ſame courſe with S. <hi>Hierome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vita ejus Ep. <hi>25.</hi> ad Aug. &amp; alibi.</note> was he not a Monk, a Prieſt, unmarried, ſaid <hi>Maſſe,</hi> a ſubject of S. <hi>Damaſus</hi> Pope?<note place="margin">Vita Ambrofit ante ejus opera. to. <hi>5.</hi> collecta ex operibus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus. See his Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gister. See his life.</note> &amp;c. Take S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> was he not a Biſhop, and in the ſame ſenſe a Prieſt, that is in your lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage a <hi>Sacrificant</hi> of the body and bloud of Chriſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married, ſubject to <hi>Rome?</hi> &amp;c. Take S. <hi>Gregory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See S. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> in his Oration of S. <hi>Baſile.</hi>
                  </note> he was not only a Prieſt unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, but a Pope, and began a Religious Order.</p>
               <p>If you go to the Greek Fathers, S. <hi>Bafile</hi> was a Monk, inſtituted a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:35857:53"/>Order, a Prieſt, a Biſhop un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married, made a form of <hi>Maſſe,</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this day by the Greek Church, &amp;c. and all theſe and the reſt lived and died in the communion of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> Ask your ſelves, whether theſe could be other then Papiſts. Take twelve men from the Seſſions in the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> put them upon the ſame teſt that you did our Prieſts, tell me what the <hi>Verdict</hi> will be. This conſideration alone is ſufficient to compell any reaſonable man to become <hi>Catholique;</hi> and to ſee that your Praelatique Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is a Bull in Chriſtianity, invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving manifeſt implicancy.</p>
               <p>I ſhould adviſe you therefore to leave the Fathers, renounce them; nay, you'l do well to make an act of your <hi>Convocation</hi> for this; and as you have new Doctrines, get new Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, your own fancies will be beſt, coloured with the name of reaſon,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:35857:53"/>though abuſively, as your more ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated wits of late have done with your allowance, as appeares in the publique approbations of <hi>Chilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Gregory Niſſen</hi> writing the life of <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>Wonder-worker,</hi> comes home to this, ſaying that there were <hi>Nonnulli qui piam &amp; ſinceram religionis doctrinam adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarent, ac per probabiles argumentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones ſe penumero etiam doctis &amp; pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus viris veritatem facerent am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguam.</hi> There were ſome who would adulterate the ſincerity and piety of Chriſtian Doctrine by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent probability of reaſon, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that even learned and prudent men would be caught by them. I would that too too many were not taken with this guilded engine to the prejudice of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>Examine whether this warrants not all <hi>Catholiques</hi> from conſenting
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:35857:54"/>to your new Articles, and all your Proſelites to leave you, for them? was it ever clearly demonſtrated to be unlawfull to continue in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Faith? nay hath not the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry been demonſtrated by arguments, and confirmed by ſuffering death for it, by learned men. You would ſeem here to have a ſenſe of the <hi>principles of juſtice, ingenuity and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity,</hi> though they are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable Pleas for perſwaſion of Chriſtianity; neither did the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles by civilities court men to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Chriſtians; yet ſome reſpect might in the beginning of your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt, and now alſo be uſed to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques</hi> upon theſe titles, ſince <hi>England</hi> received their firſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt from the Pope, and all Church endowments from them, they ſhould not in <hi>juſtice, ingenuity, and humanity,</hi> be perſecuted for theſe good deeds, as they have beene by
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:35857:54"/>you, though ſome of you I know were of milder ſpirits, and diſliked ſuch cruelties.</p>
               <p>After in the numbers enſuing you bring more motives, but they are domeſtique, within your own walls, as ſome of the former were; but as far as they have any force, more ſtrongly convince a neceſſity for the continuance or re-aſſuming of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Religion;</hi> though many of them are rather drawn from the kitchin then the Church; there is little Chriſtian Philoſophy here, but much of Praelatique policy, as from Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, fat perfonages, &amp;c. which are alſo glanced at in the former Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle. I omit alſo the joyned Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphs, being very extrinſecall to our purpoſe, and indeed to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, only ye ſeem to ſtrike at the preſent Parliament, wherein we leave you, deſiring you may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the Act of perpetuall Oblivion.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:35857:55"/>
               <p>You are indeed in the purſuit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, that Princes have Papall rights, upon condition, that you may have Epiſcopall honors and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices; you ſpeak it very plainly, and joyn them as cloſely, you plead hard alſo for Biſhops out of another topick, namely, becauſe (as you ſay) King <hi>James</hi> had learned by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that <hi>no Biſhop, no King.</hi> Our former hiſtories I believe could give ſome ſtrength to ſuch a pretence, but this kind of argumentation ever ſince your time was antiquated in <hi>England,</hi> for you were ever in true Logick, in the judgment of all the Church-Praelates (beſide your ſelves) no other then equivocally Biſhops, that is <hi>idem nomen,</hi> and <hi>ratio diverſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that it was alwaies (ſince you were concern'd in it, and now much more) acknowledged by all other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines to be <hi>ſubjectum non ſupponens,</hi> that is a ſubject which ſignifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35857:55"/>I diſcuſſe not here at large, whether it was for lack of true <hi>form,</hi> or <hi>matter,</hi> or <hi>Ministery,</hi> which are all required in true Ordination; yet you know it's hard enough to prove that you had either: your <hi>form,</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of Prieſthood, as uſed in the ſenſe of your Authors, in the more generall opinion, is not valid any more then the <hi>Arrians</hi> Baptiſm; of Epiſcopacy alſo it's dubious, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever if Prieſthood fails, Biſhops fall, <hi>matter</hi> ye reject, as not neceſſary, and therefore you keep impoſition of hands, as a ceremony only, as many among you teach; ſo that it cannot be cleared, that you had any, much leſſe all neceſſaries.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it muſt be preſumed, that here was ſome eſſentiall defect, &amp; conſequently no Ordination, if no Ordination, no Sacraments, by your ordinary Miniſtery. And from hence how many have we known, who
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:35857:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>(without your note of Apoſtaſie) have left your pretended Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and became Lay-perſons; as Souldiers, Phyſitians, and the like, according to that of <hi>Tertul. de Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip, Alius hodie Epiſcopus, cras ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us: hodie Diaconus qui cras Lector, hodie Presbyter qui cras Laicus.</hi> Some of you have indeed ſtrugled hard for your ſucceſſion from us, as the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> did, and therefore they ſuppoſed a Biſhop at <hi>Rome,</hi> from whom they might ſeem ſtill to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, wherein they did more wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then you, who judge him Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, who is your Head, according to your own Tenets; but you could never clear this imaginary title even of your Miniſtery; For firſt, though your <hi>Record</hi> were true, as touching the matter of fact in the Ordination of Archbiſhop <hi>Parker,</hi> which will never be cleared, for it is gathered out of <hi>Stow,</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz. Holinſhed,</hi> and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:35857:56"/>other Proteſtant Hiſtorians, that <hi>Parker</hi> and the reſt of your firſt pretended Biſhops were Biſhops in your account before theſe Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors returned into <hi>England</hi> (having run away in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> reigne) ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not ordained by them, and by conſequence the Record cannot be true; Yet if it were, there are many titles will render all invalid, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as touching the pretended Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainers Ordinations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hodgkinſon</hi> was one of the 26. who were inſtituted in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. his Schiſm; if he were ordained, it was by the new form, which (<hi>Sanders</hi> ſaith) the King newly preſcribed to Biſhops, and conſequently of no effect: <hi>Barlow</hi> was elected of <hi>Aſaph,</hi> and nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Menevenſis,</hi> but no man hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto prov'd, that he was at all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained; <hi>Scory</hi> and <hi>Coverdal</hi> were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected under <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. but not ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35857:57"/>by a lawfull Biſhop, as that dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and neer neighbour to thoſe times <hi>(Sanders)</hi> ſhewes. <hi>Landaff</hi> indeed was a true Catholike, though puſillanimous Biſhop; but being threatened excommunication by <hi>Bonner,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> if he ſhould ordain them, he feigned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſick, and declined the matter. And it muſt be highly conſiderable, that Biſhop <hi>Oglethorp,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carliſle, Kitchin,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Landaff,</hi> and other Biſhops never acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged them, as validly ordained: Yet if all were true, (ſince ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Divines hold, that to ordain is an act of juriſdiction; and almoſt all hold, that juriſdiction, at leaſt in the exerciſe, is loſt by depoſition or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication) the title of your ſucceſſion cannot be certain.</p>
               <p>Secondly, You ſhould be well read in the opinion of <hi>Armachanus, Panormitanus, Delphinus,</hi> which
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:35857:57"/>
                  <hi>Scotur</hi> is thought to hold probable, and <hi>Durand</hi> will not have to be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, out of S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> which if ſuppoſed, would cruſh you wholly. I only propound this to you, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſonant to your doctrine in this Act, in the Paragraph concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Epiſcopall Government,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to your ſucceſſion, becauſe by this opinion all titles except di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, which your Act challengeth not, are ſurely loſt, becauſe as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tul.</hi> in the place cited ſaith, <hi>Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones eorum temerariae, leves, inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes:</hi> wanting divine foundation, they muſt needs totter.</p>
               <p>Thirdly the confuſion at the <hi>Nags. head,</hi> witneſſed by ſuch who were preſent and afterward ſuffer'd ſevere impriſonment, for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, muſt needs make a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able argument for your nullity, theſe aver'd that <hi>Landaff</hi> having withdrawn himſelf, <hi>Scory</hi> was ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:35857:58"/>Ordainer, who laying his hands over their heads with the Bible, ſaid; <hi>Take power to preach the word of God ſincerely.</hi> So that he doing it alone, and in this only form, nothing was done, which will convince a nullity in all your firſt pretended Biſhops, and conſequently in all thoſe who have been ordained by them, which renders the whole to be invalid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot appeare that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Ordainers were not deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from theſe Parliamentary Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, as <hi>Sanders</hi> calls them, in that they ſupplicated the Parliament to confirm them, and to ſupply what was wanting, according to holy Churches Doctrine and practiſe.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Chriſtian Divinity teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us, that in the matter of <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> all are obliged to follow the more certain opinions, and to leave the leſs probable; whence it follows, that all your Proſelites are bound,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:35857:58"/>though there were ſome probability for your Ordination, to leave you, and return to us, where it is unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable, according to your confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Principles.</p>
               <p>Hence it appears in what a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous praecipice all ſouls are, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on you for Sacraments, ſince your title at the beſt is uncertaine; and how ſecure are thoſe of our Communion, even according to your principles, ſince all you pretend is from us: yet I know not whence, ſomwhat you ſeemed alſo to have in point of Juriſdiction, which belong'd to true <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and this you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed with unexemplar ſeverity, by impoſing Oaths <hi>ex Officio,</hi> &amp; the like, not only <hi>praeter</hi> but <hi>contra,</hi> Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call burthens, extremely hard to all, who did not even ſuperſtitiouſly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to you, and theſe your proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, were judg'd highly prejudiciall to the laſt King.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:35857:59"/>
               <p>But to return to your propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: it would admit a greater truth being modified according to your intention with that which <hi>Logicians</hi> call a <hi>ſimple converſion,</hi> thus, <hi>no King, no Biſhop,</hi> &amp; for this you need not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue <hi>ab authoritate,</hi> al of us wil grant it in order to you, and out of this ſelf-intereſt I ſhould almoſt conceive you wiſh the one with the other, but not a King, without a Biſhop: Your whole diſcourſe inclines to this. And for the former <hi>Aphoriſm,</hi> indeed your reformed Epiſcopacy had no ſuch influence upon the people, as to conclude <hi>no Biſhop, no King;</hi> their uxorious complexion rendred them too vulgar and contemptible: You pretend indeed much zeale for the late King, eſpecially leſt he ſhould be perjured in violating his oath of preſerving your Priviledges: But it is conceived to be a fallacy of <hi>non cauſa, pro cauſa,</hi> and grounded not
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:35857:59"/>upon <hi>amor amicitiae,</hi> but <hi>concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiae,</hi> that is, you loved him for your own ſakes, you would not have him forſweare, leſt you loſe all. So you are tender againſt ſacriledge, wheras none are ignorant that your Reformation was grounded upon it, the ruinous walls of houſes dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to Gods ſervice witneſſe it, and the Biſhopricks of <hi>Oxford, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terborough, Bristol, Cheſter,</hi> and <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> were wholly founded upon Church-rapine: But as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, ſo in this, you are ſuſpected to ſeek <hi>quae veſtra ſunt, non quae Jeſu Chriſti.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Finally ye add.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>We hope we ſhall be the leſſe blamed for our unwillingneſſe to have any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall concurrence in the extirpating of Epiſcopall Government, ſeeing of ſuch extirpation there is no other uſe i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginable, but either the alienation of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:35857:60"/>their revenues and inheritances, (which how it can be ſevered from ſacriledge and injuſtice, we leave others to find out) or to make way for the introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of ſome other form of Church-Government; which whatſoever it ſhall be, will (as we think) prove ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſtructive of, and inconſiſtent with Monarchicall Government, or at leaſtwiſe more prejudiciall to the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, orderly, and effectuall exerciſe thereof, then a well regulated Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy can poſſibly be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe were the laſt words of the dying Praelacy, and Praelatique Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy. And truly the conjunction of them is ſo weak, as being drawn <hi>à Poſteriori,</hi> and from very remote and extrinſecall topicks, that they declare your cauſe deſperate. Alas, why would you trouble your ſelves, us, and the world with a tedious contraſt about a pure fanatique I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol, which as in this upſhot appears,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:35857:60"/>had never any reall foundation, but only <hi>civitas ſolis,</hi> a pretty invented <hi>Eutopia</hi> in the Sun, where none but Knights Errant appeared in battell, and like high-drawn Meteors vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the midſt of the ayery com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, leaving ſome ill-ſavours behind them, which require ſuffumigations of ſacred incenſe, or at leaſt aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of holy Water.</p>
               <p>Theſe laſt words being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd, you quitted the ſtage; the <hi>Chorus</hi> replying ſadly.</p>
               <p>How truly may we apply to you our bleſſed Saviours inculcation to the Jewes; <hi>Quoties volui, &amp;c.</hi> you have murthered his Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles lawfully ſent to you for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 80. years, you have had their examples of Chriſtian fortitude in undergoing cruell deaths for the antient Religion of Gods univerſall Church, and of this Nation from the infancy of Chriſtianity here, and you
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:35857:61"/>would not be adviſed by them. Wherefore you are now diſſipated, and none will receive you: The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church declines you, all Proteſtant Congregations diſclaime you, which the B. of <hi>Cant.</hi> at the Councell table confeſs'd, when (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a falſe rumour of his flying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yong Seas) he ſaid, <hi>If he were minded to leave England, he knew not whither to go.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All that now remaines of your Religion within the whole Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Nation by authority, is, that among the <hi>Articles</hi> upon the ſurrender of <hi>Virginia</hi> to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments navall forces dated the 12. of <hi>March</hi> 1651. The 11. <hi>Article</hi> is this, <hi>That the uſe of the Common-Prayer Book be permitted there for one yeare enſuing, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God in nature, in all ordinate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to corruption, never ceaſeth, till the ſubject be reduced to <hi>mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:35857:61"/>prima,</hi> that is to your firſt inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, wherein you now are; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt content your ſelves to be numbred, <hi>inter non entia,</hi> for the Law ſaith, <hi>De non exiſtentibus, &amp; not apparentibus eadem eſt ratio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truly I am of opinion that future ages, which ſhall read your hiſtory, will take it to be a <hi>Romance;</hi> it ſeems ſo full of prettily contrived impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancies; like the old Romans, who endeavoured by a tumultuous noiſe of kettles to enchant the Moon; you have entertain'd this little world with high noyſes in Pulpits, in hope to enchant the Inhabitants, but the curtain being opened all vaniſheth.</p>
               <p>What God will work out of this (for generation certainly followes corruption) we yet know not, only we learn (according to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) that the more imperfect form is firſt produced, and then the more No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; as in man, firſt the vegetative,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:35857:62"/>then the ſenſitive, and at laſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Synagogue</hi> had three States even after Chriſts coming firſt it was obligatory til <hi>Chriſts Paſſion;</hi> it was lawfull, not profitable till <hi>Pentecoſt:</hi> but from thence (after ſufficient pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation of the <hi>Goſpell</hi>) it was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull every where: By theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcents, it was degraded, and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably buried. And truly ſomewhat after this manner, though not ſo handſomly in the cloſe, your Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Idol was to be adored under ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation from 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> till the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> when your Biſhops came to their purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Then the Idoll was reduced to the ſecond ſtate of being lawfull, not profitable or obligatory: this continued til the <hi>Covenant</hi> was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Parliament in <hi>Sept.</hi> 1643. From thence it became unlawfull, and ſo ingloriouſly expired, yet was
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:35857:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>not publikely expoſed in order to interment, till the <hi>Common Prayer Book</hi> was (on the 26. of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1644.) voted down by Parl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, and the <hi>Presbyterian Directory</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in its room (which is ſince alſo vaniſhed;) Moving and inviting all <hi>Catholiques, Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> to ſing the <hi>Dirige</hi> of <hi>O Hieruſalem, Hieruſalem, quae occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis Prophetas &amp;c. they ſhall not leave on thee one ſtone upon another,</hi> Luk. 19.</p>
               <p>All paſſengers will eaſily ſee the reaſon of the ruine of this high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built <hi>Babel</hi> to be, becauſe they made the walls without Morter; they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had <hi>unity, community,</hi> nor <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> which only can cement a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſtructure.</p>
               <p>The Roman world was aſtoniſht to ſee the <hi>Pompeian</hi> faction, having the conſcript Fathers of Senate joyned in and with them, to be ſo often, and at laſt totally routed: their anſwer
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:35857:63"/>which <hi>Cicero</hi> celebrates, was, <hi>Nemo mirari debet humana concilia divina neceſſitate eſſe ſuperata.</hi> The ſame anſwer in a Chriſtian ſenſe may be given, as cauſe of your ruine, Gods decrees have evacuated your ayery policies.</p>
               <p>Let me with all poſſible inſtance, and charitable ſeriouſneſſe conclude to all our Country men with S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> in his ſeventeenth chapter, <hi>de utilitate credendi,</hi> written to <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noratus,</hi> wherein he firſt ſhews the power and prejudice, which habits and cuſtomes work in us, as if he would admoniſh all to ſuſpect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and therefore ſince Religion is a buſineſs of ſo high concernment, as upon which our ſalvation radical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depends, you will do well to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, whether it is not cuſtome, rather then Chriſtian reaſon, which keeps you where you are, without duly weighing the grounds.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:35857:63"/>
               <p>Be pleaſed ſeriouſly to read and ponder S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> who had deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtudied (in this Treatiſe againſt the <hi>Manichees</hi>) your very caſe: ſee a ſummary of the grounds of true Religion, you need read no more: truly this ſole chapter well pondred and the great truths therein wel ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, are able to ſatisfie all the world, and powerfully to compell your relinquiſhing an ill-drawn pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of a Church, which hitherto you have exhibited to the world, his words are theſe;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All cuſtomes have ſuch vertue and power to win the love and affection of men, that we ſooner can condemn and detest even the things that are naught and wicked in them, then forſake and change them; and this for the moſt part comes to paſſe, when our unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full appetites and deſires have gotten a Dominion and predominancy over us. Doeſt not thou think that great care
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:35857:64"/>hath been taken about the affairs of mankind and that they are put into a good ſtate and condition, that not only Divines, but moſt learned men do ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue and contend, that nothing that is earthly, nothing that is fiery; finally nothing that is perceptible by the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſenſes ought to be worſhipped and adored for God, but that he is to be prayed unto, intreated and ſupplicated only by the underſtanding or intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power; but alſo that the unskilfull multitude of both ſexes, doth in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſo divers Nations, both believe it and publiſh it? that there is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency and forbearance of meats, even to the moſt ſlender diet of bread and water, and fastings, not for one day only, but alſo continued for divers dayes together; that there is chaſtity even to the contempt of marriage and Iſſue; that there is patience, even to the contemning of croſſes and flames; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>here is liberality, even to the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:35857:64"/>diſtribution of Patrimonies to the poor, and finally ſo great a diſesteem and contempt of all things that are in this world, that even death it ſelf is wiſhed and deſired.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Few there are that do theſe things, fewer that do them well and prudently: yet the people do approve them, hearken to them and like them, yea they love and affect them, and not without ſome progreſs of their minds towards God, and certain ſparks of piety and vertue: they blame and reprehend their own weakneſs, and imbecility that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do theſe things: this the divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath brought to paſſe by the predictions of the Prophets, by the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and Doctrine of Christ, by the voyages of the Apoſtles, by the Contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melies, croſſes, bloud, and death of Martyrs; by the laudable and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent lives of Saints, and by miracles done at convenient times, in all thoſe things worthy of ſo great matters and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:35857:65"/>vertues. When therefore we ſee ſo great help and aſſistance from God, and ſo great fruit and increaſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; ſhall we make any doubt or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion at all of retyring into the boſome of that Church, which, even to the confeſſion and acknowledgement of mankind, from the See Apoſtolique by ſucceſſion of Biſhops, hath obtained the ſoveraignty and principall authority? Heretikes in vain barking round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, and being condemned, partly by the judgement of the people them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, partly by the gravity of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, partly alſo by the majesty and ſplendor of miracles, unto which not to grant the chief place and prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, is either indeed an extream im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, or a very raſh and dangerous ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancy; for if there be no certain way for the minds of men to wiſdome and ſalvation, but when faith prepareth and diſpoſeth them to reaſon; what is it els to be ungratefull unto the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:35857:65"/>Majeſty for his aid and aſſiſtance, but to have a will to reſiſt an authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which was gained and purchaſed with ſuch labour and pains? and if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very art and trade, though but baſe and eaſie, reqires a teacher or Maſter that it be learned and underſtood; what greater expreſſion can there be of raſh arrogancy and pride, then both to have no mind to learn the booke of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine myſteries from their Interpreters, and yet to have a mind to condemn the unknown?</hi> Thus far this glorious Saint.</p>
               <p>Here we ſee how highly neceſſary bleſſed S. <hi>Augustine</hi> judged it for all Chriſtians to adhere to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church in all points of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, which he declares here to be the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> that is to ſay, that univerſall multitude of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, which acknowledgeth <hi>Rome</hi> for their head; whoſe authority, as he ſaith, is confirmed by conſent of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:35857:66"/>
                  <hi>Nations, Councells, and Majeſty of Miracles:</hi> Was ever your fictitious Church thus adjuſted?</p>
               <p>Here great S. <hi>Augustine</hi> puls down ſails, and of a Maſter glories to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Scholler: Whence we learn, that if an <hi>Origen</hi> (the crums of whoſe plenty rendred <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus</hi> rich in the eſteem of all) or an <hi>Apollinarius</hi> (with his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts againſt <hi>Porphyry</hi> and other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of Gods Church) or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prodigious Comets of wit and learning, or whatſoever poſteriour Maſters (who can be but pedants to the former) ſhould preſume to teach the Church, or to queſtion her Magiſteriall Dictates or Conciliary Decrees, we muſt ſay with <hi>Vinc. Lyr. ca.</hi> 10. <hi>that with the Church we ought to receive Doctors, and not with Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors to forſake the faith of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Could we attaine to S. <hi>Paulins</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:35857:66"/>contempt of our ſelves, we ſhould not at ſo high a rate, as to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of Gods Church and his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truths, ſell our raw conceits: S. <hi>Hierome</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> made high eſteem of his learned and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Epiſtles, and S. <hi>Amand</hi> kept them as Diadems in his Storehouſe, whereof he ſent to S. <hi>Paulin</hi> a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, to which he replies, <hi>Legimus in tergo epiſtolae annotationem epistola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quas meas eſſe indicatis: nam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rè prope earum omniumimmomor eram ut meas eſſe non recognoſcerem, niſi vestris literis credidiſſem, unde majus accepi documentum charitatis veſtrae: quia plus me vobis quàm mihi, notum eſſe perſpexi.</hi> If he had been tickled with our vanity, he would have kept a better bed-roale of his writings in his memory, then to borrow, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unwillingly, from S. <hi>Amand</hi> a knowledge of his own works. Here is no danger of recalcitration in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:35857:67"/>to the holy Churches great trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury opportunely diſpenſed, and humbly received by her learned chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> (our Grand Maſter) puts all Doctrine and Doctors to the teſt thus: <hi>If any preach unto you other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then you have received, be he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed?</hi> It's high time therefore to leave <hi>Pope Celestine</hi> his golden rule, celebrated in <hi>Lirinenſis; let novelty ceaſe to moleſt antiquity;</hi> for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he is, or of whatſoever emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency for learning or ſanctity he ſeems to be, if he introduceth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty; <hi>alienus eſt, prophanus eſt, hoſtis est;</hi> he is a wolfe in a ſheeps cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>What greater expreſſion can there be of raſh Arrogancy and pride, &amp;c.</hi> as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath taught us.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="critique">
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:35857:67"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A curſory Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion upon</hi> Henry Fernes <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> of the Diviſion between the Engliſh and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church upon the Reformation.</head>
            <p>IF I had not ſeen the two Capitall letters <hi>D. D.</hi> in the title page of his Treatiſe, I ſhould have eſteem'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not worthy taking more notice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f then of a ſcurrilous Pamphlet, neither dare I play the Cabaliſt to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive the divers ſignifications of thoſe Hieroglyphicks, but reading them
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:35857:68"/>without notes they import <hi>Doctor of Divinity,</hi> the Preface, a Country Sermon, which ever muſt have a fling at the Papiſts; neither that nor the enſuing diſcourſe is <hi>ad Clerum,</hi> els they would more ſavour of the <hi>Doctor,</hi> according to the antientſtle of the Univerſity.</p>
            <p>In his ſaid preface (to take notice firſt of ſome of his calumnies there) he falls into theſe expreſſions. <hi>All the Chriſtian world ſees how long the poor distreſſed E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtern Church has lain under that heavy condition, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitied by them of the Romiſh Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and how they have ſtood affected to us ſince our Reformation, has ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently appeared by their ſeveral pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes againſt us; what hand they had in our preſent troubles, is not unknown to ſome; what joy they now take in them, let their own hearts tell them, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His chiefe ayme in the book is to ſhew, that the arguments which they
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:35857:68"/>uſe to condemn the <hi>Independents</hi> are not retortable upon themſelves by us; and what greater uſe of reaſon they grant to their Proſelites, then we: All which he labours for in the ſeventh, and the enſuing <hi>Sections,</hi> till the thirteenth, wherein verily he is ſo unhappy, that any child may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn his arguments with great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; His reſult being this, that <hi>private judgement, or judgement of diſcretion</hi> (which he allows to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men) muſt ſubmit to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, els the power of <hi>Juriſdiction muſt proceed to judge, cenſure, and caſt out the diſobedient;</hi> and therefore he exacts (even in caſe of errour) all <hi>externall peaceable ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</hi> Did ever the Roman Church go thus far? was there ever challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged any higher captivation of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, then that every one ſhould ſubmit to the publique? Was ever externall ſubjection exacted in
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:35857:69"/>point of error, which this <hi>D. D.</hi> wil have in his Church.</p>
            <p>Further the Independents (whom he involves with <hi>Sacrilegists</hi>) he wil have inexcuſeable in their breach from them, becauſe it was not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by a <hi>Nationall Synod,</hi> as theirs, which how untrue it is, all know; for all the Biſhops of this Nation were excluded and impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned when the Doctors party firſt decreed the breach from their old Mother Church, as the very Acts te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie; ſo that they had no more <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Synod,</hi> then theſe, who can when they pleaſe, congregate as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their party, and ſtile it a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Synod,</hi> eſpecially if warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Parliament, as the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have lately done, whom he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually rejects.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he ſayes the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, or Sectaries (as he calls them) have not <hi>plain and evident Scripture,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:35857:69"/>but places unlearnedly wreſted:</hi> Who knows not that the Prelatiſts could never hitherto bring Scripture or antiquity, except <hi>places unlearnedly wreſted?</hi> have not we demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this 100. times? do not they ſtand regiſtred upon this accuſation in all Courts of Juſtice, equity, and reaſon, and yet are not able to wipe off the leaſt part? Theſe are <hi>D. D.</hi> his peculiar Aphoriſmes, which by a little redargution, riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt himſelfe and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>The other Sections are built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Topicks, as common as <hi>Robin Hoods</hi> Song, and anſwered by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Stationers Catalogue of <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort Mart,</hi> therefore I trouble not the judicious Reader with the rehearſall.</p>
            <p>But to return to the words cited out of his Preface, it is moſt evident to all who read hiſtories, what
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:35857:70"/>pains the Roman Church hath, and doth take, in maintaining Colledges and ſending Miſſionaries for the reducing of the Eaſtern Church; and with what affection and ſolicitude ſhe laboured the recovery of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to her priſtine Religion, does clearly appeare by the innocent bloud of many of her Prieſts ſhed at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> and other places of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique execution, meerly upon that account, which is the only practiſe he can juſtly accuſe the Roman Church of: &amp; what hand we Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes have had in the preſent troubles of the Land, cannot be unknown, but to thoſe that are truly ſimplicians, &amp; of very ſhort conſideration, when our Prieſts, being every where throughout the Countrey ſince the beginning of the late warres, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned and perſecuted to death, and our Layty ranſackt almoſt to utter ruine in point of temporall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:35857:70"/>only upon the ſcore of their old Recuſancy, no one of them could be hitherto convicted of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiariſme, notwithſtanding the extreme eagerneſſe of their enemies to accuſe them upon any cavill that malice could ſurmiſe; let the <hi>D. D.</hi> convince me of the contrary by any particular inſtance, if he can: On the other ſide, what hands and heads, what pens and Pulpits thoſe that were not Catholiques have had in their own and our late trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, the Parliamentary Records, <hi>Scaffolds</hi> and <hi>Gallowſes</hi> do make ſo evident, that none can pretend ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, but ſuch as have their ſculs ſtuffed with <hi>Fern.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we joy in our Adverſaries troubles, is another unproveable calumny of the Doctors. We doe extremely pitty them, and hope that the Divine permiſſion of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity of Sects, and ſubdiviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:35857:71"/>them, may ſooner bring them to reflect on their common Schiſme, and of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord to endeavour a re-union with the root, whence they ſeparated themſelves.</p>
            <p>But I preſume, when the <hi>Doctor</hi> has read the foregoing diſcourſe, he will ingeniouſly confeſs, who were the only cauſe of our late troubles; or if he will ſtill ſeem to be wilfully ignorant, let him inform himſelf further of the <hi>Scotchwomen</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denborough,</hi> who flung their ſtools at the late <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Legat's</hi> head, that came to put in practiſe his new <hi>Service Book,</hi> and other innovations there in the year 1639. I his bred the firſt diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, and gave the Alarum to all the ſad enſuing troubles in both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as our modern hiſtories una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly agree.</p>
            <p>It would ſeem ſtrange that a grave
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:35857:71"/>
               <hi>D. D.</hi> ſhould nor be ſenſible of the ſin of calumny againſt ſo celebrated a Church, but to reproach her with want of charity, or rather exceſſe of malice, (in joying at their neighbors ſpiritual ruines, which by all poſſible ſolicitude ſhe hath laboured to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent,) and to accuſe her Members, as Boutefeus of State: But this is the Prelatiſts conſtant ſtile, ſince they were diſpoſſeſt of true charity by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing Schiſm; neither do I know what ſhould move them thus to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from the innocent, but deſpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 89. line 19. for <hi>ſalved</hi> read <hi>valued.</hi> p. 96. l. 15. r. <hi>Decrees.</hi> p. 106. l. 16. r. <hi>Parſonages.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
